<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christian meditations vpon eight Psalmes of the prophet Dauid. Made and newly set forth by Theodore Beza. Translated out of French, for the common benefite, into the vulgare tongue by I.S.</title>
            <title>Chrestiennes méditations. English</title>
            <author>Bèze, Théodore de, 1519-1605.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1582</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 109 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 61 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09772</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 2004</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120270</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855469</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855469</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20964</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09772)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20964)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 411:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christian meditations vpon eight Psalmes of the prophet Dauid. Made and newly set forth by Theodore Beza. Translated out of French, for the common benefite, into the vulgare tongue by I.S.</title>
                  <title>Chrestiennes méditations. English</title>
                  <author>Bèze, Théodore de, 1519-1605.</author>
                  <author>Stubbes, John, 1543-1591.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[120] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Bacon house, by Christopher Barker, printer to the Queenes most excellent Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1582]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation, by John Stubbs, of: Bèze, Theodore de. Chrestiennes méditations sur huit psaumes du prophete David.</note>
                  <note>Publication date from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Beza vpon the penitentiall psalmes.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G H⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms --  English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20964:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20964:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Chriſtian meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons vpon eight Pſalmes of the Prophet Dauid. Made and newly ſet forth by Theodore Beza.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated out of Frenche, for the common benefite, into the vulgare tongue</hi> by I. S.</p>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London in <hi>Bacon houſe, by Chriſtopher</hi> Barker, printer to the Queenes moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Maieſtie.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:20964:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20964:2"/>
            <head>To euery Chriſtian Reader, <hi>and namely to the Lady Anne</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con, now wife to Sir Nicolas Bacon Knight.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Truſt (Madame) the alone names of Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid and Beza, which is the honourable ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of this litle booke, will not alone pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure it a reuerende welcome into your hands, but withall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all men will both warrant and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the tranſlators price to be woorth his labour, as that which will recompence his fewe ſpent houres, with the much profite and pleaſure of many. For, beſides the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon helpe it brings to all, for more cleare underſtanding and expounding thoſe eight pſalmes: it is ſingularly medicinable to wounded and caſt downe conſciences, who after their labor ſome combate with ſinne, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd profitable humiliation there through, nay againe by theſe ſweete Meditations <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>riſe with ioy, finding happie iſſue of their
<pb facs="tcp:20964:3"/>troubles. And this, as it was my ſimple iudgement vpon firſt reading, euen ſo is it my comfortable experience vpon reading and reading againe. Which was one thing that made me, among others, to thinke of you, good Madame, as to whoſe tender conſcience it might be welcomly applyed. But what neede that holy Prophet, and this reuerend Paſtor, this my worde of poore credite? It is as if the leaſt Pleiade would affoord ſome poore helpe of light to Sunne and Moone: I muſt learne there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to come downe, and know mine owne place, acknowledging my ſelfe to borrowe or begge both light and credite from them, if I may be vouchſafed but the fauour of a ſtammering trucheman to ſo worthy an Hebrew, and to ſuch a Frenchman. Vpon both whoſe warrantiſe (as it were) a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble voucher, I wholy relye and reſt ſecure for ſufficient approofe of the matter of my tranſlation. Nowe a worde or two for this dedication, wherein my choiſe was not ſo much to content my ſelfe, but to goe rather as neere as poſſible to the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Authours own verie meaning. He firſt purpoſed it to a Ladie, preuented by her death, gaue it yet to a Ladie, &amp; that to a Ladie <hi>Anne Bacon,</hi> wife to that Lorde late of great honour, &amp; for euer of Chriſtian fame, Sir <hi>Nicholas Bacon</hi> Knight, father to Sir <hi>Nicholas Bacon</hi> Knight, huſband to this Ladie <hi>Anne Bacon.</hi> Being therfore by this meanes ſtill continued in the ſelfe ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ne of the Ladie <hi>Anne Bacon,</hi> wife alſo to
<pb facs="tcp:20964:3"/>Sir <hi>Nicholas Bacon,</hi> and that in the ſame houſe, ſo néere, as from fathers wife to ſonnes wife: I halfe preſume vpon, and yet humbly crane leaue of that learned La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die <hi>Anne Bacon,</hi> to whom the Authour did firſt appropriate it, that as ſhee was once one with the father, and by him hath déere pledges: So ſhée will not thinke this any impropriation, but in her good affection to all that houſe, ſuffer them to receiue by her the honour of ſome particular intereſt with her in ſo ſweete a labour of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour: who in his Epiſtle makes moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable memorie of her huſbande, and giues teſtimonie of good reputation to her ſonne. Although therefore, I confeſſe my ſelfe of verie duty to loue al that good Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therhoode, firſt for their loue to the trueth, with other agreeable vertues of wiſedome and true honeſtie, and then for that loue which it pleaſeth euery one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (I wote not howe without my merit) kindly to beare me: yet in giuing this to their eldeſt brothers wife, and ſo to them all, I neither giue them nor pay them ought, but yéeld them their owne, and which I might not haue giuen to any other, vnleſſe beyond the right of a tranſlator, I would haue taken vpon me to tranſlate that into a ſtrange familie, which ſeemes as a very heirloome properly belonging to <hi>Bacon</hi> houſe.</p>
            <p>So wiſhing you (good Madame) moſt happie going forward in a ſimple hearted profeſſion of Gods Eoſpell to the good en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſample of your owne houſhold, and a ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb facs="tcp:20964:4"/>light among your neighbours: I the leaſt of them, beſeech the Lorde Ieſus to bleſſe you and Sir <hi>Nicholas,</hi> together with his meaſe of religious brethren, ſo as growing in faith and loue, they may be a faſt holding bundle of brethren in Chriſt, who keepe you all euer his, and one anothers. From Th. <hi>31.</hi> May. <hi>1582.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours verie faithfull to command, <hi>I. S. S.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20964:4"/>
            <head>To my lady, the lady Anne <hi>Bacon, widowe of the deceaſed Syr</hi> Nicolas Bacon Knight, Lord Keeper of the great ſeale of England.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Adame, among other bookes of holy ſcripture, that of the Pſalmes wel deſerueth to bee ſingularly recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to vs. It is nowe ſome time, ſince hauing beſtowed ſome payne in tranſlating and expounding the ſame, I gaue my ſelfe alſo to take ſome more libertie of dealing with them by way of meditating vpon that ſubiect, chooſing (as it were for an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaye) the ſeuen Pſalmes called ſome time <hi>Penitential,</hi> becauſe they were appointed to ſuch as after hauing ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied open and canonical penaunce, were reunited to the body of the Church: wholy doing it for my par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular
<pb facs="tcp:20964:5"/>inſtruction and conſolation. After this, beeing required by a great &amp; vertuous princeſſe, to frame for her ſome forme of prayers: I tooke them afreſh into my hands, poliſhing them ouer, and that with hope of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing them: which being letted by the ſodayne deceaſe of that Lady, I reſerued them among my papers as things of no great price: where they had lyen ſtill, had not bene the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of maſter Anthony Bacon your ſonne, into theſe partes: whom when I ſawe to take pleaſure in this litle piece of woorke, and againe know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the latin letters wherewith it hath liked you to honour me, the great and ſingular, yea extraordinarie gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces wherwith God hath indewed you, and whereof I acknowledge a very paterne in your ſaid ſonne: I perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded my ſelfe that it ſhould not be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing
<pb facs="tcp:20964:5"/>to you, if this ſmall vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume carying your name vpon the browe, were offered to you, in teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of the honour and reuerence I beare to the vertue of you and yours: hoping withall that this eſtate of widowehode whereunto it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God to call you by deceaſe of that right vertuous and of right renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Lord, my Lord Nicolas Bacon your huſband, &amp; moſt worthy Keeper of the ſeale of England, you might perhaps therein finde ſome conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, after the reading of thoſe great and holy doctors Greeke and Latine ſo familiar to you, for your better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming in the meditation of ſpiritual things, and in this conſtancie and Chriſtian patience wherewith God hath ſo beautified you, that in you is verily acknowledged that Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anly high minded courage which I
<pb facs="tcp:20964:6"/>ſawe in theſe partes ſhining in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed, of very happy memorie, Syr Anthony Cooke Knight, during thoſe great calamities publique to the realme, and particular to him &amp; his whole familie. See the ground of my purpoſe, which if it may pleaſe you to take in good part, which I very humbly craue, it may be perhaps an occaſion of proceeding in this buſines, our Lord ayding, whom I beſeeche, Madame, that increaſing in you his greateſt graces, he will preſerue you and all your verie noble familie, long in all holy and perfect prosperitie. From Geneua this firſt of Nouem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. Anno. 1581.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours very humble and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiceable to commaunde,</hi> Theodore Beſze.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:20964:6"/>
            <head>¶A Meditation vpon the firſt Pſalme of Dauid.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>1</hi> Bleſſed is the man y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> doeth not walke in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> counſayle of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked,</note>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Las poore wretch &amp; moſt caytife creature, which art neuer more reaſonles then when thine own blinde rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon carieth thee, and when thine owne too too vnruly will doeth driue thee. What way wilt thou chuſe in this maze of manifolde pathes, wherein thou wert borne, and through which thou haſt wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered vagabondlike till nowe? Thy firſt path of infancie, what better name can I giue it then brutiſh ſimplicitie, which fooles call In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocencie, a way full of foule vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleannes, and an heape of miſeryes, amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g which this is one of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt,
<pb facs="tcp:20964:7"/>that the infant can neither fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee miſeries comming, nor through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conceiue them beeing preſent. From this path whither entredſt thou oh vnhappy? Ahlas, into that wilde deſert of youth, a deſert I ſay, well tracked and throughly beaten euery way, in which neuertheleſſe there was neyther right waye nor path, and yet notably haunted with moſt miſchieuous witches. There found I vanity that old ſorcereſſe, &amp; ſhe would needes be my guide, offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring me at our firſt acquaintance a thouſand co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentations in appara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, but more vayne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> winde in effect. There did thoſe two wilde beaſts, Ouerweening &amp; Ambition, make themſelues ſo tame &amp; familiar with me, as I was by &amp; by at their becke, ſo farre forth as to followe them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſea that had neither bottom nor
<pb facs="tcp:20964:7"/>ſhoare, where they did their beſt to make me dwell ſtill remedileſſe, &amp; all (quoth they) to bring me to the true felicitie: in ſteade whereof I was betrayed into the haudes of pleaſure, that nice &amp; decked ſtrum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, and withall the moſt ſtinking and daungerous that euer was in the world, inticing and interteining infinite wayes all them which doe but looke at her, and which more is, ſhe bewitcheth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſuch ſort with her cuppe, that ſodainely their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience becommeth lulled a ſleepe, all iudgement loſt, yea very ſenſe it ſelfe aſtoniſhed, and then loue wee our woe, &amp; loathe our weale, what is moſt foule, ſeemes moſt fayre, what is moſt hurtfull, ſeemes moſt profitable, and that which is moſt ſowre, ſeemes moſt ſweete, yea of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes it bringeth to foule death
<pb facs="tcp:20964:8"/>and ſhame, and a thouſand woes &amp; weale away: and this is all the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie to be hoped for. Oh moſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py man which balkeſt this ſtreight, and ſingleſt thy ſelf farre from ſuch &amp; ſo vnhappy feloweſhip. But woe is me,<note place="margin">nor ſtande in the way of ſinners,</note> I haue done yet worſe then al this, for, going foorth of the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, I am entred into an other cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey peopled with farre worſe folke then the former: for hitherto I haue rather bene deceiued then a decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and that I erred, proceeded not ſo much of malice, as of ignorance. But from thencefoorth in ſteade of hauing learned by mine own harme I nowe gaue my ſelfe ouer to doe much worſe, applying my ſelfe to couetouſnes, enuie, deceit, and at once, to euery kinde of vice, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading my ſelfe that this was the true and neereſt way to happineſſe.
<pb facs="tcp:20964:8"/>And when ſometimes my conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce reproued me, I ſought by al meanes to make my ſelf beleeue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vice was vertue, couetouſnes was nothing but good huſbandrie to prouide for my ſelfe and my meany, enuie was nothing with me, but a deſire to haue of things about me as other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had, al deceit was faire cunning &amp; good ſkil: at a word, I concluded that being in this world, I muſt do after the facions of other men, vnto whoſe example I framed my ſelfe throughout. But poore wanderer, what haſt thou founde in the ende of this ſo ill a way? verily all the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to thy weening. Nowe then howe bleſſed is that perſon which buſieth not himſelfe to folow ſuch a way of folke giuen vp to all vice, bringing toyle to our body, torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to our conſcience, and final deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:20964:9"/>both of body and ſoule! For whither doth ſuch a cuſtome of ill doing thruſt vs by litle &amp; litle?<note place="margin">Nor ſit in the ſeate of the ſcorne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</note> Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly euen to this point, that wee loſe all feeling of God, all remorſe of conſcience, of ignorant wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come wicked, of wicked we become miſchieuous to the vttermoſt, and finally we become ſcorners of God and of euery good thing. Oh moſt great God, is it poſſible that duſt &amp; aſhes being now become ſo infirme a creature, ſo changeable, ſo very nothing worth, yea worſe then nought, ſhould ſo doate in preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as not only not to quake at the leaſt aduertiſement of his own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, being awakened of it ſelf or by any the leaſt meane in the world: but alſo to ſet him ſelfe againſt thee, to ſhut his eare againſt the voyce of thy threatnings, to pluck out his
<pb facs="tcp:20964:9"/>owne eyes, that he might not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue thy horrible iudgements, to harden his heart againſt thine al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie puiſſaunce? Oh moſt good God, &amp; patience it ſelfe, thou louer of men, in ſo much as thou diddeſt not ſpare for their ſake thine onely ſonne equall to thee, yea one ſelfe God with thee, can it come to paſſe, that this creature, deſpiſing thy goodnes in calling him when hee fleeth, thy patience in bearing with him when he rebelleth, thy liberali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in making him a partner of thy ſo great and incomprehenſible bliſſe euerlaſting, when he gaue himſelfe to moſt vaine vanitie, ſhould ſo far forget himſelf, as to reiect thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, to make a mocke at thy patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, to trample vnder his feete ſuch a treaſure? Yea Lorde, alack, all this is but too true: and which is more,
<pb facs="tcp:20964:10"/>thoſe which bee guyltie of theſe crimes, be ſuch as thou haſt aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced higheſt. But O my God, retire my feete from thoſe crooked wayes wherein I haue gone too farre al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready: and ſince thou haſt put in me the deſire of bleſſedneſſe, ſhewe me alſo the ready addreſſe thereunto, giue mee a will to follow it, and ſtrength to purſue it, euen till I may attaine it to thine honour and glorie.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>2</hi> But his delight is in the law of the Lord, and in his law doth he meditate day and night.</note>2 Now then poore creature, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſed by thy ſelfe, and miſlead by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, hearken at the laſt what the Lord will teach thee, Bleſſed is that man which taketh pleaſure in the Lordes law, and which meditateth thereof dayly and nightly: what ſay I, Thy law Lord? why, that is it which aſtoniſheth me, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth me, which killeth me, as
<pb facs="tcp:20964:10"/>wherein there is neuer a comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement which carieth not my death ſentence withall. For, howe many creatures haue I ſet in thy place? oh golde and ſiluer, thou haſt occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied a great part of my heart and of mine hope: ye honours and world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pleaſures, haue bene the god which I haue adored: oh abuſed heart, thou haſt bene the altar wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on haue bene ſet vp ſo many idoles as thou haſt paſſionate affections, whereunto thou haſt thralled thy ſelfe. The whole courſe of my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate life hath bene a continuall diſhonour of thy precious name. Howe many times haue I ſworne vntruly and bene diſloyall? Who can reckon the leaſings which make me faultie euen before my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours? When haue I ceaſed from mine owne works to do thine? Thy
<pb facs="tcp:20964:11"/>worde (Lord) what deafe eare haue I giuen it, and howe haue I practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it? Holy Baptiſme wherewith thou haſt vouchſafed to honour me, hath it not bene a thouſand times by me diſhonoured, polluted, and villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſly abuſed? O how vnworthily haue I preſented my ſelfe to thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly boord! How oft haue I lyed vnto thee! And can I boaſt of any obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience towardes them where I owe it, ſince I haue ſo litle feared to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obey thee? If in thy ſight, O iuſt Iudge, hee bee a murtherer which ſayth to his brother Racha, if he bee an adulterer which caſtes a looke at his brothers wife with a luſting eye, then howe can I cxempt my ſelfe from either of theſe crimes? And yet neuertheleſſe according to thy moſt iuſt lawe, there is no atone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for blood among men: howe
<pb facs="tcp:20964:11"/>then ſhall I compound for ſo many murders towardes thee, O thou iudge of the verie thoughts? If luſt alone without any further act doe make me an adulterer, and if no ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ulterer haue any part in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen, poore creature that thou art, what ſhall become of thee? If it be not onely ſimple thieuerie, but, which more is, flat ſacriledge, to withholde goods conſecrated to thy glorie, (according as thou haſt committed them vnto vs from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue to be thy ſtewards of them) how may I bee diſpenſed withall, hauing ſhut mine eares leaſt I ſhould heare the poore, cloſed mine eyes that I might not ſee him, loc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vp my bowels that they might not be touched with compaſſion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſo many my poore brethren? What ſay I, my brethren? Nay ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:20964:12"/>towards thee thy ſelf, O Lord, hungring, thirſting, and being na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in their perſon. Thee I ſay, oh thou great and eternall ſonne of God, which haſt made thy ſelfe of no reputation, that thou mighteſt aduaunce man ſo high with thee, which vouchſafedſt to be come poore to the end to enrich him with eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall treaſures, which didſt ſubiect thy ſelfe to all our weakneſſes, that thou mighteſt make vs inuincible: at once, (oh depth of bountie) thou diſdaynedſt not to hang naked on the croſſe, &amp; to enter into the houſe of death, to the end to cloth me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine with glorie, and to bring mee into the true paradiſe of euerlaſting life. To be ſhort, who is it but man that holdeth thy truth in vnrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, that is a lier, and a falſifier, and that is borne with luſt: And
<pb facs="tcp:20964:12"/>wouldeſt thou, Lord, that I ſhould ſearch life in thy lawe, which is the verie ſoliciter, witneſſe, iudge, and executioner of the deadly ſentence agaynſt me? All this notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding (oh Lord) there will I ſeeke life, ſince that ſo is thine ordinance, and there ſhall I find it, ſince thou haſt ſpoken it. Thy law is good be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is giuen by him that is only good: it is holy, for it is made by the holie of holies. From that which is good cannot proceede that which is ill: death commeth not properly by the lawe, but through ſinne: ſinne commeth of the ſinner, and not from thee, who doeſt hate and forbid that which is naught. If a ſicke man would freat himſelf to death againſt the Phyſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whoſe were the fault? The lawe then iudgeth me becauſe it findes me guiltie: O good Lord,
<pb facs="tcp:20964:13"/>cleare mee againe, and make mee guiltles by thy law of faith, that the lawe of workes (which amaſeth me, condemneth me, &amp; ſlaieth me in my ſelf) may aſſure me, abſolue me, and quicke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me by him that hath fulfilled it for me, &amp; became euen curſe it ſelf for my ſake: For, Lorde, it is thou which ſtrikeſt and cureſt, which lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt to graue &amp; bringeſt back again: Grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t me through him the ſpirit of ſanctification, which may fit mee vnto thy ſeruice, create in me the will and the power to doe, pearce mine eares that in hearing I may heare, giue me eyes to ſee, grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t me feete to walke in thy wayes: Then Lord, being wholy changed, I ſhall not heare thy worde for fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions ſake, but I ſhall therein take all my pleaſure, I ſhall eate I ſay with a good appetite of this quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kening
<pb facs="tcp:20964:13"/>foode, for I ſhall finde a good ſmacke in it: I ſhal digeſt it, and neuer thinke my ſelfe ſatiſfied with it: Day and night I ſhall not ceaſe to applie all mine vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thereunto, that more and more I may be nouriſhed and ſuſteyned in the full enioying of that true, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute, and eternall felicitie.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note n="3" place="margin">For he ſhalbe like a trée pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the riuers of waters, that will bring forth her fruit in due ſeaſon:</note>
               <hi>3</hi> In meane while, O Lorde my God, ſhall I be idle, and finde leyſure to do nothing, but onely to occupie my thoughts in contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation? Not ſo: for though he be nothing leſſe then idle which exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſeth that part of him ſelfe recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from thee, to knowe thee and conſider thee in thy word and in thy workes, and that no mans actions can be conducted but by the good diſcourſe and reſolution of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: yet foraſmuch as man was crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:20964:14"/>at the beginning, and ſince that time againe made a newe creature by thee the ſecond time, to be a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular inſtrument in thine hande, it is neceſſarie that his ſoule beyng taught by thee, ſhoulde imploye it ſelfe, and that inſtrument which thou haſt giuen it, in ſuch actions as are agreeable to thy will, and in that vocation, for which thou haſt created it. If then the idle body be guyltie in thy ſight, as by good right the workman may finde fault with that toole, which wil not abide to be handled, yea he may marre it and breake it: what ſhalbe thought of that toole, that wil occupy it ſelfe as it liſteth, and when the workman would vſe it, it will not be ſtirred? and when you woulde handle it of one ſide, it will turne it ſelfe quite awke? Be this farre from mee my
<pb facs="tcp:20964:14"/>God, ſince thou haſt facioned and framed mee. For rather will I be not an inſtrument of a dead matter, but I ſhall haue a naturall &amp; liuely ſtrength in me,<note place="margin">Whoſe leafe ſhall not fade:</note> which I finde alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to come vpon me. To be ſhort, I ſhalbe as a faire fruite bearing tree, planted by thine hand in thy houſe, grafted vpon that right and kindly O liue, ſhooting vp to heauenward, my freſh greene braunches garni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with fruites proceeding from thy grace,<note place="margin">So what ſoeuer he ſhall do, ſhal proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</note> which will alway water mee at the roote, and will preſerue from froſtes, heates, windes and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tempeſtes, ſo as from them I ſhall rather gather freſh forces to yeelde plenteous fruite: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as finners ſhall bee drye at the roote.<note n="4" place="margin">The wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked are not ſo, but as the chaffe, which the winde dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth away</note> And if they make any gay ſhewe for a while, yet in the tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of an hande they come downe
<pb facs="tcp:20964:15"/>either by themſelues, or ſtriken by thy furie, and ſhalbe rooted out, ſo as no man ſhal perceiue their place, neither ſhal they be good for ought, but to bee burned and brought to nought: And yet do I ſome wrong to compare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to trees, rather are they thornes, bryers and brambles, which thou doeſt fagot vp together in their time, to be thruſt in the fire: yea rather yet ſhall they be as duſt &amp; ſmall chaffe, which ſhall go into the winde, when thou ſhalt fanne thy floore, and ſhalt locke vp the good grayne in thy garners.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <note n="5" place="margin">Therfore the wicked ſhall not ſtandin the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, nor ſinners in the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblie of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</note>
               <hi>5</hi> And albeit this difference be not manifeſt through the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſions of this worlde, but contrariwiſe the wicked men ſeeme ſureſt planted, hyeſt promoted, and moſt floriſhing, yet ſhal not this vayne ſhewe be du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, but the true iudgement of
<pb facs="tcp:20964:15"/>their eſtate ſhall ſhewe it ſelfe, ſo ſoone as thy iuſtice appeareth to ſet in order all that is diſordered: and it ſhall then he clearely diſcouered in deed what they are, when that great day ſhall come, ſo dreadfull to the wicked, which ſhall not know whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to turne them, and ſo longed for by thy poore ſeruants, to whom being gathered together from all coaſtes, thou ſhalt doe iuſtice and reaſon of ſo many wrongs and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lences receiued, wiping away their teares, and graunting them that felicitie which they ſo much deſire.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <note n="6" place="margin">For the Lord kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth the way of the righteous, &amp; the way of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſhall periſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note>
               <hi>6</hi> Nowe then my ſoule, ſith the francke bountie of thy God hath drawen thee forth of theſe ſtraying paths of deſtruction, to the ende to leade thee in the true and only way of bleſſedneſſe: take good heede not to forſake it, but followe on thy
<pb facs="tcp:20964:16"/>courſe liuely, ſuffer not thy ſelfe to be miſlead by any inticements, nor to be diſmayed by any threatnings, holding faſt alwayes this concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in thine heart, as well agaynſt flatteries as againſt terrifyings, to wit, that howſoeuer the matter fall out, ſince that God is God &amp; Iudge of the world, they which go ſtreight cannot miſſe to be bleſſed, ſtanding alwayes in the good grace and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of God: and the wicked contrariwiſe muſt needes periſh.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:20964:16"/>
               <head>¶ The ſixth Pſalme me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditated.</head>
               <p>
                  <note n="1" place="margin">O Lorde rebuke me not in thine an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, neither chaſtiſe me in thy wrath.</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>H, woe is me more then miſerable wretche, aſſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, preſſed, outraged on all ſides, wounded mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally by my conſcience, pearced through and through by the touch of infinite treſpaſſes, and nowe at brincke of that deepe dungeon of deſpayre, in my body euerwhelmed with euils, plunged in ſorrowes, in which torment nothing more can be founde that may adde to my torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: what ſhall I doe, what ſhall I ſaye, whither ſhall I goe? what may I finde in my ſelfe but the ſubiect of ſuffering, and the cauſe of that I ſuffer, and who ſhall ſuccour mee from els where? If I looke into heauen, I ſee there my iudge: The
<pb facs="tcp:20964:17"/>ſunne, that great eye of the worlde, which hath ſeene me ſo often to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend his maker and mine, doth ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon me, and ſeemes to giue light to the worlde for none other pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe but to behold me whileſt I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure theſe my merited paynes. The night which ſeemes to couer all things els with her darkenes, alas, what doth ſhe witneſſe againſt me? Forſooth me ſeemes, ſhe hath dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled her darkenes in a loathſome deteſtation of that which in glimpſe of her accuſtomed obſcuritie ſhee hath bene forced to perceiue in me: It yrketh the earth to beare ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happie a creature, and already ſhee openeth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> great throat of her gulfe to ſwallow me in, and to redemau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d my ſelfe to her ſelfe, as hauing too much abuſed that earthly matter which ſhee miniſtred to my maker
<pb facs="tcp:20964:17"/>when he facioned me. All that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment which I receiue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other creatures, is giuen me onely to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine me in this extreme torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Death it ſelfe recules fro mee, leſt ſhe might giue at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt ſome ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſnes of dolor to this miſerable bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, by diſpatching it at once out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way. As for me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they be either mine enemies, or els ſuch friends as haue no might to giue me remedie: whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhal I go the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? what ſhal I ſay? what ſhall I doe? I will euen goe ſtreight to thee, O eternall: For what good ſhal it do me to runne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from him that is euery where? Who ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hide me from before him, which ſeeth euen that that is not? &amp; what creature, though it could, yet durſt vndertake my quarrel w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thee? &amp; if it ſhould vndertake, what would enſue, but their ruine and mine?
<pb facs="tcp:20964:18"/>And my diſeaſe being incurable to all others ſaue to thee, to whome ſhould I haue recourſe but to thee? Nowe then, eternall God, more great then greatnes it ſelft, behold him that is leſſe then nothing, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the greateſt ill bee ſomething. O creator of man, beholde thy crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture quite diſfigured: O louer of man, beholde him that hath conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with thine enemie againſt thee: O perfectly good, behold him that is conceiued and borne in vice: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde the drye wood to the conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming fireward, and ſhall it yet be ſo hardy as to ſpeake? His miſerie conſtrayneth him to ſeeke remedie: thy goodnes declared in thy promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and verified by ſo many experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, doeth open his mouth to cry before thee, <hi>Reproue me not in thy wrath, correct me not in thine an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20964:18"/>O God, which haſt ſayde, that the waye not to bee iudged, is to iudge our ſelfe, beholde this vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie man, that acknowledgeth before thee &amp; thine Angels, before beauen &amp; earth, that my leaſt fault of a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſande is worthie of thy wrath ſo dreadfull, that none can beare it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is none thy match.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>2</hi> Haue mercy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me, O lord, for I am weake: O Lord heale me, for my bones are vexed.</note> 2 And what emboldeneth mee then after this ſort: Thy goodneſſe, thy pitie, thy compaſſion, which is ſo much the greater as it ſtretcheth it ſelfe vpon the vnworthie, &amp; there moſt aboundeth, where there is moſt ſinne. O Lorde, ſuffer mee, though duſt and aſhes, to bee, not bold in my ſelfe, but aſſured in thee. O euerliuing God, I haue learned in thine houſe by thee, and in my ſelfe by thy grace, how thou haſt an anger of a moſt gentle father, and a
<pb facs="tcp:20964:19"/>wrath of a moſt ſeuere Iudge. I am worthte of this, but I be ſeeche thee turne it from me, for it deſtroyeth: I refuſe not the other, becauſe it buyldeth vp: for thou chaſtiſeſt whome thou loueſt. Nowe then Lorde, ſmite, but keepe in the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of the blowe. And to ſpeake in a worde, O eternall God, haue pitie on me. For who hath neede of grace, but the guyltie one? Who beggeth comfort, but the afflicted: or phyſicke, but the ſicke?</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>3</hi> My ſoule is alſo ſore troubled: but Lord how long wilt thou delay:</note> 3 And againe, who can raiſe the poore man ouerwhelmed vnder the burden of ſinne, beaten downe flat vnder thy puiſſant hande, cruſhed bones and all, caſt away in his own conſcience, but thou, O great God, who by thine onely word giueſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to all that is: Confirme then that which remaynes of thy nature
<pb facs="tcp:20964:19"/>and being in me, or rather worke a newe, that which otherwiſe goeth away &amp; is vndone. And howe long, O my God, wilt thou ſuffer mee thus to languiſh: How long ſhall I cry without being relieued: Howe long ſhall I wayte for thy mercie? Suffer, O Lord, that the vehemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of dolour may vſe this laguage, ſubmitting it ſelfe yet wholly to thine onely good and thriſe good pleaſure.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>4</hi> Returne, O Lord: de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer my ſoule: ſaue me for thy mercies ſake.</note> 4 O eternall God, I ſay, turne againe to mee that countenance, which with one looke can reuiue the dead: Lay forth that great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion to heale my ſaynting ſoule: for vpon thine onely grace it is that I ground my requeſt.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>5</hi> For in death there is no reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of thee: in the graue who ſhall praiſe thee?</note> 5 O God, thou knoweſt what a deſire I haue to be an inſtrument of thy glory, and to employ what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer
<pb facs="tcp:20964:20"/>it may pleaſe thee to make mee to publiſh thy prayſes. Alas, Lord, my ſinnes thus ſending me to death, ſhall they be able to hinder this my purpoſe that comes of thee? For, being dead and lying in the duſt, loe all my purpoſe broken off, my memory ſhall forthwith bee taken quite away, my tongue ſhall ſpeake no more of thee, my mouth ſhal ceaſe to haue any being: To be ſhort, this poore corps being for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done, wherein ſhall it ſerue either thee, or my neighbours? Moreouer Lorde, if I do not onely dye, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as is thine ordinance for all men to dye once, but alſo that I dye as one ſmitten in thine ire, Oh my God, my God, howe can I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber thee in that laſt neceſſitie? How can I call vpon thee at my greateſt neede? To ſpeake at once, what ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:20964:20"/>become of me wofull creature, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to a Iudge that condemneth mee, yea euen already executeth his ſentence vpon mee? Oh God, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue mee from this woe of woes, and giuing me againe for this time life to this poore body, aſſure my poore ſoule by witneſſing vnto it, that thine anger is ceaſſed, to the ende that death when it ſhall come, be not a meſſenger of terror, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may bring tydings of felicitie forthwith to be enioyed.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>6</hi> I fayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in my mouruing:</note> 6 Alas Lorde, as thou haſt now had an eye, and ſtraightly marked our ſinnes, which thou doeſt nowe make me throughly to feele: ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider this poore creature now chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, condemning that which hee hath too long approoued, yea iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging himſelfe, which is the very meane not to be iudged of thee: for
<pb facs="tcp:20964:21"/>ſo it pleaſeth thee, ſith thou haſt teſtified it both by thy word and by effect. I haue long ſlept in ſo many vnhappie pleaſures,<note place="margin">I cauſe my bed euery night to ſwimme, &amp; water my couch with my teares.</note> nowe can I ſleepe no more by reaſon of ſighing. O ye nightes, heretofore witneſſes of a thouſand thoughtes wickedly imagined, and of the vnhappy ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quele of thoſe thoughts, be ye now witneſſes of my waylings. And thou my bed, a bed earewhile of reſt very ill employed, be thou through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly moyſtened nowe, and ſwimme thou with my teares.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>7</hi> Mine eye is dunined for deſpite, &amp; ſunke in becauſe of all mine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies.</note> 7 Oh thou ſunne, whoſe light I haue heretofore ſo much offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, (and howe could I feare to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend thee, being ſo deſperatly bolde as to deſpiſe thy maker and mine, looking into the depth of heartes, and to aſſay to put out his light in me?) O thou Sunne, I ſay, whoſe
<pb facs="tcp:20964:21"/>brightnes I am vnworthie to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde: mine eyes being iuſtly puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, can no more ſee thee, being ſoaked out and drawen drye by the teares that they haue ſhead: they be, I ſaye, quite worne with yrke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomnes and heauines, whereof they bene witneſſes that vexe mee. But what, ſhall I periſh then? Is there no more hope? Am I quite without recouery? No, no, my God: For whence comes this bewayling of my ſinnes? This hatred of my ſelf? This confidence to call vpon thee? this deſire to amend? From whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſprings it, that I ſpeake yet, and can call thee my God? Certainely it is thy grace: For whence comes any good, but fro thee? O mightie God, howe be thy wayes incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible! May it be thine yre which ſhould quiet me, or mine heauineſſe
<pb facs="tcp:20964:22"/>that might cheare mee? Or can my death bee the occaſion of my life? No, no, my God, this benefite pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedes no whitte of any worke of mine, but Lord, in working againe him that as much as in him laye, hath vndone himſelfe, thou ſheweſt thy ſelfe to be the ſame that madeſt all things of nothing, and canſt pul light out of darkeneſſe. Grance then commeth from thee vnto mee, to driue my ſelfe out of my ſelfe, that ſo againe I may finde my ſelfe and all my weale in thee.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>8</hi> Away from me al ye workers of iniquity: for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde hath heard the voyce of my wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping.</note> 8 You then mine enemies, which weened to haue caſt mee flatte and quite to the grounde, ſhall you dare now to ſhewe your faces any more? Thou malicious Sathan, the firſt author of all ill, what gayneſt thou to haue throwen me lowe, vnleſſe it be that thereby my victorie againſt
<pb facs="tcp:20964:22"/>thee is more notable? For, thou ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, maugre thy malice, that God will triumphe vpon thee by my fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe. Oh, and out vpon my ſelfe the moſt dangerous enemie to my ſelfe, yeelde thy ſelfe to him, againſt whome the more thou haſt reſiſted, the more neere thou cameſt to thy deſtruction. You curſed men, whoſe trade is to doe ill, and you which haue ſo perſecuted mee, I ſtand no longer in feare of you.</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>9</hi> The Lord hath beard my petitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: the Lorde wil receiue my prayer.</note> 9 For the eternall God, which ſeemed to haue caſt mee off, and to deliuer me into your handes as one vtterly reiected, hath heard my deepe ſighes accompanyed with teares:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>10</hi> Al mine enemies ſhalbe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded &amp; ſore vexed: they ſhalbe turned back, &amp; put to ſhame ſuddenly.</note> The euerliuing God hath heard my prayers, the eternall will perſeuere to heare my ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p n="10">10 And conſequently all mine
<pb facs="tcp:20964:23"/>enemies which haue bene ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous, goe their wayes with ſhame: I ſee them already quite forlorne, they ſhalbe fayne to leaue their vngratious enterpriſe to their reproche, a chaunge ſo much the more wonderfull, as it commeth to paſſe ſuddenly and beyonde all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The 32. Pſalme meditated.</head>
               <p>
                  <note n="1" place="margin">Bleſſed</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>H my God, where ſhall that true felicitie bee found, which vngracious men weene to finde? Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly man findes it not within him ſelfe. For who is he that can ſaye, hee is without ſinne in his ſoule? And where there is ſinne, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe there is malediction alſo. And
<pb facs="tcp:20964:23"/>for the body, what man is ſo brutiſh, that can perſwade himſelf, the moſt ſoueraigne good ſhoulde fall into a lumpe ſubiect to ſo many euils and miſeries within and without, brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging it at length alſo to death? This felicitie then is out of our ſelues, and we muſt begge it from otherwhere. And from whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce? To ſeeke it among beaſtes were more then beaſtlike, and conſequently much leſſe will it be founde in the ſenſeleſſe creatures. O golde and ſiluer, ſo highly valued with men of no value for wit, how ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you make a man happie, ſith your beſt ſeruice to a man ſtandeth in leauing him, &amp; to paſſe to another, &amp; that tarying w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him, you bring him nothing but care to keepe you, feare to loſe you, and an vnſatiable deſire to hoarde you? Thou foode, whoſe taſte holdes
<pb facs="tcp:20964:24"/>not the ſpace of halfe a foote in all mans body, and cannot be felt, but while it is in looſing, which canſt not nouriſh but with thine owne corruption, which art moſt commonly the inſtrument of mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and finally of death, canſt thou bring bliſſe to a man? You celeſtiall circles turning about endleſly, is it true that mans happy or vnhappy ſtate hanges vpon your influences? How ſenſeleſſe were he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo would thinke, ſith you your ſelues muſt ſuffer cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge? And being ſuch as you are, you ſend vs to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knowledge of one farre greater, vpon whom you your ſelues depende. You ſpirituall creatures ſo excellent, ſhal it be you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhal furniſh vs of this goodly feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie? You be happie in deede &amp; very puiſſaunt creatures, &amp; yet but crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, &amp; therefore alſo vnable to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire
<pb facs="tcp:20964:24"/>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> image of God in me, (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which I muſt remaine vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie) as to ſay trueth, it is not your woorke, but for God alone: neither were you created to beſtow on me y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which you haue not your ſelues re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, but by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> free goodnes of him that is greater then you, &amp; then all things elſe. And if I find none elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, neither aboue, nor belowe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> can giue me in part or in whole, that which I ſeeke, ſhould I bee ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyd of vnderſtanding, as to thinke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I can giue it to my ſelfe? Shal I find bleſſednes in corruption, iuſtice in vnrighteouſneſſe, life in death? For what am I Lord in my ſelf but corruption, but vnrighteouſnes, but death? Alas then, ſhal I periſh? For out of al doubt, death is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wages of ſinne. But y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> caſe ſo ſtands, O God, that no euill is incurable to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie.
<pb facs="tcp:20964:25"/>He which hath drawen all things out from nothing, can he be hindered to make againe his owne work? He that cauſed light to come out of darkneſſe, ſhal not he bring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> death to life? Yes certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, otherwiſe death being y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, might thruſt God out of his ſeate. Nowe then, Lord, my diſeaſe being paſt cure of all creatures, I come to thee, who canſt doe all that thou wilt: and who haſt ſhewed yet more excellent teſtimonie of thy goodwil in ſauing man, then thou diddeſt of thy might in creating him. Thy might ſurely was witneſſed by a meane wel becomming thee, when thou madeſt all of nothing, framing man to thine image and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: and this ſame infinite power appeares clearely in the conſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all thy creatures. But what
<pb facs="tcp:20964:25"/>is all this in compariſon of that worke, mans Redemption?<note place="margin">is hee, whoſe wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe is forgiuen, &amp; whoſe ſinne is co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered.</note> Bleſſed then is he, not ſimply whome thou haſt created, (for man turned this bleſſing of creation into an aſſured curſe by ill vſing it but rather is he bleſſed, whome thou haſt ranſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med through ſuch a great goodnes of thine, as euery way excels. For leſſe vnworthy of thy gratious bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is hee, which yet hath no being, then is the ſinner: And thou conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedſt not thy ſelfe (O great deapth of goodneſſe) to reſtore to ſinnefull man that bliſſe which hee had loſt, but thou gaueſt him a farre better: For hauing created him ſuch a one, as by ſweruing from his perfection (as in deede hee did) might fall alſo into ſinne, death, and curſe, thou fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally makeſt him ſuch a one by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, as hee can neyther ſinne
<pb facs="tcp:20964:26"/>nor dye, but is bleſſed for euer. O ſtraunge thing, O great and chiefe maſter worke of God! Al wretched<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe comes by ſinne, and yet none comes to happines, but hauing paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed firſt and formoſt by ſinne: not that bliſſe comes out of ſinne, but becauſe mercy preſuppoſeth miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, pardon a fault, and quickning a former death. But whence comes this pardon? From thy ſelfe, O Lorde, and from thy pure bountie.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note n="2" place="margin">Bleſſed is the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord imputeth not iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</note>
                  <hi>2</hi> And howe? euen by quitting me my tranſgreſſions, by couering my ſinnes, and by not reckoning vy mine iniquities: yet muſt thy iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be ſatiſfied euen wholy and to the vttermoſt. Here beholde againe a depth of wiſedome and goodnes: For howe great is that ſecret, nowe manifeſted by effect, where pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all, thou yet puniſheſt all, and
<pb facs="tcp:20964:26"/>we hauing payed nothing, yet finde our ſelues to haue wholy ſatiſfied thee? Iudgement is become mercy to vs: out of malediction thou dre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt bleſſing, &amp; death hath brought foorth life. All this was thy doing, O God, infinitely great and euen ſo good: for who alſo coulde haue done it, but thou? thou haſt done it, becauſe it pleaſed thee, for, who knewe thee, who loued thee, who gaue vnto thee firſt? That Emma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuel conceiued by the holie Ghoſt, hath fully repaired in himſelfe this poore nature conceyued in iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. This righteous pledge hath ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed all righteouſnes for vs. The ſuertic that ought nothing, hath payd for our diſcharge. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore then troubleſt thou thy ſelfe poore conſcience? That corruption wherein thou art, is blotted out in
<pb facs="tcp:20964:27"/>the holy of holyes, conceyued and borne for thee. The obedience of the acceptable one, with the fulneſſe of his obedience, hath filled euen til it ouerflow againe, this want of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, which thy Creator re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth of thee. The ſuffrings of the iuſt of al iuſtes are thine acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Beholde thy life and thy feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie: there is none elſewhere, there is, I ſaye, none other Ieſus, that one and onely name of ſaluation. What remaynes then, but that cheerefully without gloſſe, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faynedly acknowledging thy ſelfe to be in death, thou receiue this life by a liuely faith, liuely, I ſay, whoſe effects may ſhewe themſelues.<note place="margin">And in whoſe ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit there is no guyle.</note> For beſides that God can not bee decey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, hee is no ſauiour of deceyuers. The God of trueth hateth all falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood: and who doth waſh himſelfe,
<pb facs="tcp:20964:27"/>to the ende to returne to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> filth? Is pardon giuen that we ſhould ſinne more hardily? Doeth light bring vs into darkeneſſe? And as no fitter ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of all this may bee, then my ſelfe: euen ſo will I publiſh it,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>3</hi> When I helde my tongue, my bones con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, or when I roared all the day.</note> to the ende that I may ſerue for a mir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and paterne to others. Alas, in what paine was I? Were not all my bones dryed with heauineſſe? Was there euer ſommer drought more partching, then this heate, which hath vtterly marred mee? Howe oft haue I bene ouerwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with anguiſh, not able to vtter one worde? How often on the other ſide,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>4</hi> For thine hande is heauy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me, day &amp; night: and my moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture is turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the drought of ſummer.</note> haue I cryed and howled all the day long?</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4</hi> And not without cauſe, my God, for daye and night I felt the terrible weighing ſtrokes of thine hande, a burden intolerable for any
<pb facs="tcp:20964:28"/>creature. But howſoeuer I toſſed &amp; tormented my ſelfe, where found I remedy at length? Hearken here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to euery one, and thou my ſoule for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get it neuer.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>5</hi> Then I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged my ſinne vnto thee, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hid I mine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie: for I thought, I wil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe againſt my ſelf my wickednes vnto the Lord, and thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaueſt the puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of my ſinne.</note>
                  <hi>5</hi> So long as I ſought to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe my ſelfe, and couer my faultes in all or any part: So long as I went about to counterbalance my faultes with my payne, ſo long as I ſpurned againſt the ſpurre, my miſchiefe grewe ſtill: I haue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore learned a farre other waye. I come to thee, O eternall God, my Iudge and my aduerſe partie, I haue confeſſed all, I haue ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed nothing in ſilence, nor diſguiſed any of mine iniquitie: and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as I did purpoſe it in my ſelf, euen ſo haue I done: condemning my ſelfe I found abſolution, &amp; ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moning my ſelfe I was diſmiſſed.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20964:28"/>
               <p n="6">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>6</hi> Therfore ſhall euery one, that is godly, make his prayer vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee in a time, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d: ſurely in the flood of great wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters they ſhall not come neere him.</note>
                  <hi>6</hi> Nowe then, all ye not hautie and high looking ones, but whome God hath vouchſafed grace to taſte his goodneſſe in afflictions, aboue all in the combats of conſcience, ſearche for this onely and moſt aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red remedy. Haue recourſe to him which ſmiteth you: the meane to finde him is prayer. Let not your vnworthines hinder you, but rather let it driue you ſo much the neerer him. With God he is counted wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie, which confeſſeth himſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie. Yf ſinne diſpleaſe thee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is ſinne, and that thou deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt his grace, knowe that already thou art halfe heard: For, true ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe to haue offended, deſire to come before him, and an affection to cry him mercy, be ſo many meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers whereby he inuiteth thee firſt, and ſo many teſtimonies that
<pb facs="tcp:20964:29"/>he wil be found to thee. Come then and enter, but with an heart ſtric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken downe, with an head bowed low, and thou ſhalt feele all thy tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vaniſh away, all thine angui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes flee as farre from thee as euer they were nigh thee: that flood of euils which had couered and ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed thee, ſhall voyde it ſelfe.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>7</hi> Thou art my ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret place: thou pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueſt me from trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: thou compaſſeſt me about with ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</note>
                  <hi>7</hi> Shortly, in ſteade of this mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie thou ſhalt receyue the true peace which the worlde can neither giue, nor take away, and the true repoſe of conſcience, euen the very anchre and earneſt peny of that du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable bleſſedneſſe to followe. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely my God, this is true, for, I knowe it by experience, and ſhall learne it more and more, hauing thee for my Protector, giuing mee euery day new arguments to praiſe thee, by continuall aſſiſtance of thy
<pb facs="tcp:20964:29"/>fauour, O my deliuerer,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>8</hi> I will inſtruct thee, and teach thee in the way, that thou ſhalt goe, &amp; I will guyde thee with mine eye.</note> as agayne on my part thou onely art, and ſhalt be my refuge and recourſe.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <hi>8</hi> Learne this leſſon hardily of mee, thou, whoſoeuer deſireſt to knowe the right way, and bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to take mee thy guyde in this behalfe.</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>9</hi> Be ye not like an horſe, or like a mule which vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not: whoſe mouthes thou doeſt binde with bit &amp; bridle leaſt they come neere thee.</note>
                  <hi>9</hi> Beware you take not the bit in your teeth, nor kicke like mule and horſe: for ſo doe beaſtes voyde of vnderſtanding, and thou ſeeſt them gayne nothing by ſo doing, ſaue that they are bitted ſo much the more roughly, and ſpurred more ſharpely, till they come to ſome order:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>10</hi> Many ſorowes ſhal come to the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked: but he, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truſteth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, mercy ſhal compaſſe him.</note> Euen ſo will it befall him which will not profite by ſuch cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſements from God, waxing obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately opinionate in his euil, which ſhall bring ſorowe vpon ſorowe:
<pb facs="tcp:20964:30"/>whereas on the contrary, who ſo will haue recourſe to God, bowing vnder his puiſſaunt hande, ſhall bee compaſſed with his goodnes.</p>
               <p n="11">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>11</hi> Be glad ye righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and reioyce in the Lord, and be ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full all ye, that are vpright in heart.</note>
                  <hi>11</hi> O you louers of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, you which by Gods grace giue your ſelues to vprightnes, vp, cheare vp your ſelues with mee to honour God eternall, &amp; witnes ye by your ſonnets of prayſe, that the iſſue of afflictions, on their behalfe which can make profit by them, is ioy and conſolation to the glory of that great God, which chaſtiſeth his owne for their good, and puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth the hard harted with al rigour after their demerits.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:20964:30"/>
               <head>A meditation vpon the 38. Pſalme.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>1</hi> O Lorde, rebuke mee not in thine anger, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſe me in thy wrath.</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Eternal (for to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall I addreſſe my ſelfe but to thee who art as puiſſaunt to heale as to ſmite) giue me leaue to bewray my complaint: not to playne me of thee, who doeſt nothing but well, and whoſe ire, I confeſſe I haue pulled vpon me, for my treſpaſſes: but to beſeech thee, that according to thy promiſes thou wilt not vſe againſt me that iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which thou reſerueſt for ſuch as thy fury and moſt fearefull in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation will quite deſtroy: But rather thy fatherly maner of chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing howe rough and ſharpe ſoeuer it may ſeeme to this fleſh.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2</hi> For thine arrowes haue light vpon me, and thine hand lyeth vpon me.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>2</hi> And thou woteſt well Lord, that I crye not as doe thoſe deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate
<pb facs="tcp:20964:31"/>ones, which make much of a litle, and crye loude for a ſmall griefe: For it is euen deepe to the quicke that the keene heades of thine arrowes ſhot off at mee, haue pearced: It is in very great earneſt, that thy mighty hand is (as it were) ſetled vpon me.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>3</hi> There is nothing ſound in my fleſh, becauſe of thine an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: neither is there reſt in my bones be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of my ſinne.</note>
                  <hi>3</hi> Regard, Lord, this poore bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy which hath no whole part: Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect theſe poore grynded bones: for in deede how might they ſtande, or haue any being before thine angry face? And all, Lorde, neuertheleſſe moſt iuſtly, ſince the whole cauſe thereof is in me who haue ſo much offended thee:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>4</hi> For mine iniquities are gone o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer mine head, &amp; as a weightie burde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are too hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie for me.</note> I confeſſe and auow that it is ſo, and loe, the ſpring of all ſorrowes and torments wherein I am ſowſed ouer head and eares, &amp; vtterly ouerwhelmed vnder this loade, a loade farre to heauie and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together
<pb facs="tcp:20964:31"/>together inſupportable, if thou doeſt not ſuſtayne and ſtaye me.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>5</hi> My woundes are putrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of my fooliſhnes.</note>
                  <hi>5</hi> Thoſe killing blowes which thou gaueſt mee, haue bred corrupt matter, ſuch as putrifyeth my poore carkaſe, which euen ſmelles of the fruites and hyre of my folye, poore ſenſeles man that I was, when I thus rebelled againſt thy will.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>6</hi> I am bowed, and crooked ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſore: I goe mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all the day.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>6</hi> But, beholde O my God, I will not ſtiffen my necke, I bowe both body &amp; heart vnder thy ſtrong hande,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>7</hi> For my remes are full of bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in my fleſh.</note> drawing my legges after mee, parched and broyled as I am through heauines and languiſhing. Alas, my reynes howe they burne, To be ſhort, O my God, what ſhal I ſaye?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>8</hi> I am weakened and ſore broken: I roare for the very griefe of mine heart.</note> I am altogether made up into ſorrowe, I am brayed as in a morter, I am ground as it were in a myl, ſo as I can not hold, but cry, or roare rather.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20964:32"/>
               <p n="9">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>9</hi> Lorde, I powre my whole de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire before thee, &amp; my ſighing is not hid from thee.</note>
                  <hi>9</hi> But O my Lord, (for I know thou alloweſt mee for thy ſeruaunt though neuer ſo miſerable) for all this thou art my retraicte, my lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging is after thee alone, without ſearching ſuccour elſewhere.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>10</hi> Mine heart pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth: my ſtrength ſaileth me, &amp; the light of mine eyes, euen they are not mine owne.</note> My gronings direct the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to thee, albeit thorough mightye griefe my ſeely forlorne heart had with it ſelf a thouſand wandering diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and my force ſo farre forth fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led me, as I loſt my ſight.</p>
               <p n="11">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>11</hi> My lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers &amp; my friendes ſtand aſide from my plague, &amp; my kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſtand a farre off.</note>
                  <hi>11</hi> And yet a greater griefe, when as my wretched plight ſhould rather haue moued the very ſtones to compaſſion. They which in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer tymes had called them ſelues my friendes, and whoſe part I thought it to partake my calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, they ſtand ſtone ſtill in ſtead of running vnto mee: yea my next of kinde moſt vnkindely with much a
<pb facs="tcp:20964:32"/>doe vouchſafe to looke at mee, while others,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>12</hi> They al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, that ſeeke after my life, lay ſnares, and they that goe about to do me euill, talke wicked things and imagine deceit con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually.</note> to whoſe wiſh I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not dye ſoone ynough, lay ſnares for mee, deſiring nothing but my death, not ceaſing in meane while to ſlaunder me, and to aſſay al meanes of trapping me.</p>
               <p n="13">
                  <hi>13</hi> All this notwithſtanding, thou knoweſt, Lord, that I haue not ſkirmiſhed againe with them, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring euil for euil either in deede or worde,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>13</hi> But I as a deafe man heard not, &amp; as a dumme ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which openeth not his mouth.</note> but haue paſſed ouer all this geare as if I had bene deafe not hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a whit of it, neither haue I replyed no more to them then a dumbe man which had neuer vſe of tongue: I anſwered nothing,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>14</hi> Thus am I as a man, that heareth not and in whoſe mouth are no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofes.</note> but appoſed onely ſilence to al wrongs: not that I had not iuſt defenſes y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowe, but I had rather referre all to thee, O protector of Innocents, &amp; reuenger of the oppreſſed: know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:20964:33"/>full well, that ſilence and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience pleaſe thee woonderfully well.</p>
               <p n="15">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>15</hi> For on thee, O Lord, do I waite: thou wilt heare mee, my Lord, my God.</note>
                  <hi>15</hi> Nowe then, O eternall, God, it is thou alone on whome. I wholy wayte. O Lord, thou art my God, and therefore wilt not, I knowe, leaue mee vnanſwered: For,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>16</hi> For I ſaid, Heare me, leaſt they reioice ouer me: for whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my foote ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth, they extol them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me.</note> (quoth I to my ſelfe) is it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for thee to indure that theſe miſchieuous ones which aſſay to hinder the effect of thy promiſes, that theſe vnkinde men which aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayle thee in ſetting thus vpon my perſon, ſhould haue matter to glad them againſt me?</p>
               <p n="17">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>17</hi> Surely I am rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to halt, and my ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer before me.</note>
                  <hi>17</hi> Make ſpeede then to me my God, otherwiſe I goe in danger neuer to bee reſtored, being ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed with dolours, which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company me day and night.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20964:33"/>
               <p n="18">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>18</hi> When I declare my paine, &amp; am ſory for my ſinne,</note>
                  <hi>18</hi> For my part, I am alwayes ready to acknowledge my treſpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, the payne whereof I cary with me, tormented in body, and frighted in ſpirite.</p>
               <p n="19">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>19</hi> Then mine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue and are mightie, &amp; they that hate mee wrongfully are many.</note>
                  <hi>19</hi> Mine enemies quite contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, enemies, I ſay, without all co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of cauſe, ſtrengthen them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and beare their heads higher and higher, fiercely and brauely a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt mee, who, alack, did neuer ought to them but well,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>20</hi> They alſo, that rewarde e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil for good, are mine aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> and againſt whome they thus band themſelues for none other cauſe, but for that I doe not as they doe, but rather I loue that which is good, howſoeuer otherwiſe I be a ſinner.</p>
               <p n="21">
                  <hi>21</hi> And therefore, I eternall God, forſake mee not,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>21</hi> Forſake mee not, O Lorde: be not thou farre from mee, my God.</note> but keepe thy ſelfe neere this poore creature, which calleth vpon thee, O Lorde, from whome alone I wayte for
<pb facs="tcp:20964:34"/>deliuerance,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>22</hi> Haſte thee to helpe mee, O my Lord, my ſaluation.</note> make ſpeede to ayde me in the extremitie of my neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A meditation vpon the 51. Pſalme.</head>
               <p>O God, which haſt ſet before vs in one and ſelfe ſame perſon of Dauid, a very maruaylous exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of ſinne and repentance, and of thy compaſſions: giue mee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding and good conſideration of his waylings, well to apply them to mine owne vſe and thy glorie. What is it then, that Dauid ſayth, beyng wakened by the voyce of thy Prophet Nathan?</p>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> God, O God? And dareſt thou name this moſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred name, thou miſchie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous mouth of ſo miſchieuous a
<pb facs="tcp:20964:34"/>man? hauing polluted thy ſelf with ſo many adulterous kiſſes, foule mouth, vndertakeſt thou to name it thou enemy of al vncleannes? Thou trayterous tongue agaynſt thy faithfull ſeruant Vriah, canſt thou pronounce this word, GOD, who is moſt true? Yee handes embrued with many murders, preſume you ſo farre as to followe that bolde tongue, heauing vp your ſelues to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde him, whome you haue ſo ſhamefully profaned? Thou heart, guiltie of the whole lawe broken at one blowe, art thou ſo hardie as to addreſſe thee to him, who hath alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy iudged thee? O king, ſo many wayes periured againſt him, that of a poore ſhepheardly boye, promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thee aboue the throne of all this worldes monarches: Thou hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite towardes him, who hath per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
<pb facs="tcp:20964:35"/>formed thee infinitely more then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hee promiſed thee: wretched man, which haſt trampled vnder feete the couenant of eternall life, to make an adultereſſe of a chaſte wife: vnhappie man, who haſt layd that moſt pretious name open to the blaſphemies of infidell nations: O thou ingrate, which haſt rendred to thy loyall ſeruant death for his wages: O thou vnworthy one, that, where thou owedſt to thy people all iuſtice, haſt ſhewed them the way to all miſchiefe: liueſt thou yet, ſpeakeſt thou yet? dareſt thou call vpon thy God yet? Yea, my God, ſo great is thy patience, that it giues me heart againe, not to name thee by waye of complaynt againſt mine enemies, as in ſome other Pſalmes I haue done: but euen my ſelfe to bee mine owne accuſer
<pb facs="tcp:20964:35"/>and iudge againſt my ſelfe. In ſumme, what can he, or what wil he ſaye, who was once thy deare Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid by thy more then moſt liberall bountie, but nowe is nothing like Dauid, through his owne more then moſt deteſtable ingratitude? In ſumme, I ſay, he ſayeth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1</hi> Haue mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me, O God, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy louing kindneſſe: according to the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſions put away mine mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities.</note> Haue <hi>pitie on me, O God of mercy:</hi> and what maner of pitie? True it is, Lorde, that thy mercy is alwayes infinite in it ſelfe, but ſuch is the multitude of my treſpaſſes, that ſurely me thinkes one onely mercy woulde not bee ynough for mee: wherefore I beſeeche thee, vnfolde here all the ſtore of thy compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that I may feele them.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>2</hi> Waſh me throughly from mine iniquitie, &amp; clenſe mee from my ſinne.</note>
                  <hi>2</hi> Alas, I haue not nowe to treate for the wiping out of ſome petie blot, or prancke of youth: but my foule filthineſſes &amp; pollutions
<pb facs="tcp:20964:36"/>be ſo vile, ſo ſtinking, ſo farre can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kered within mee, euen to the very ſoule of my ſoule, that, although with one word thou canſt al things, yet doe I perſwade my ſelfe, that as I may ſaye, it is not with once fairely touching that this my blotte wil away, ſo great is my rebellion, but I muſt bee rubbed and rubbed againe, waſhed and rynſed, before I can bee cleanſed from ſo great and feſtered a pollution.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>3</hi> For I knowe mine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, &amp; my ſhine is euer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me.</note>
                  <hi>3</hi> I diſſemble not, I ſet no gloſſe on the matter: I acknowledge mine iniquities, euen ſuch as they are: my wickedneſſe continually preſents it ſelfe before my poore ſpirite: me thinkes I doe euen ſtill ſee with mine eyes that poore wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man bayning her ſelfe: mee thinkes I ſee Dauid troubled in ſpirit, and while he reſiſteth his conſcience, to
<pb facs="tcp:20964:36"/>receiue thine enemie and his owne into his boſome, yeelding himſelfe his willing captiue: mee thinkes I yet ſee thoſe, whome I did vſe in that buſineſſe, alack, too too obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſeruants were they to ſo euill a commandement: I ſee, woe is me, the filed and defiled bedde whereat once I imbraced both ſinne and death: I ſee thee thou diſloyall and murderous heart, and thou trayte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous hand whereby thoſe two mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous letters, and that at ſeuerall times were written, not with ynke, but with the blood of that poore guyltleſſe ſeruant: I ſee the poore people, for whome thou oughteſt to haue layde forth thy life, nowe like a forlorne heape thruſt foorth to the enemies ſworde: I ſee thee, O my loyall ſeruant, ouerthrowen on the grounde, hathing thee in thy blood
<pb facs="tcp:20964:37"/>ſhedde in his ſeruice, that betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thee to death: I heare (as it were) a peale in mine eares of the horrible blaſphemies co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming from infidell mouthes, which I my ſelfe haue opened: I ſee that gaye mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, vnder vayle whereof I wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to vayle my adulterie, diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring it yet in meane while euen by that very meane before thee, O Lorde, and before men. Ahlas, what can I perceyue in the leaſt of theſe foule crimes, but thy wrath, thy iudgement,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>4</hi> Againſt thee, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee onely haue I ſinned, &amp; done euil in thy ſight, that thou in apeſt be iuſt when thou ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt, &amp; pure when thou iudgeſt.</note> death, and the nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt hell.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4</hi> For what get I hereby, that being the King, men dare arraygne or iudge mee according to the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the lawe againſt blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, adulterers, and murderers? It is thou, and none other, with whome I haue to doe: for it is thou
<pb facs="tcp:20964:37"/>properly that I haue offended, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whoſe eyes and tribunall ſeate that is come to light, which I ſo carefully cloaked before men: ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is to bee feared, leaſt I being thruſt downe to hell by thee, any man might rightfully ſaye, Thou haſt vnſpoken thy promiſes made to mee, or that thy worde were not aſſured: for, it is I that haue falſed my faith, and made my ſelfe moſt vnworthy of thy grace: yea verily, and for my condemnation, and thy iuſtification, what neede it come to reckoning vp of thoſe faults?</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>5</hi> Beholde, I was borne in iniquitie, &amp; in ſinne hath my mother conceiued me.</note>
                  <hi>5</hi> From the moment, my God, of this poore creatures conception, euen already had coruption cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched holde: from that time, I ſaye, that my mother hauing conceyued mee, did giue mee liuing heate in her wombe, vice was come within
<pb facs="tcp:20964:38"/>me, as the roote which ſithence hath brought foorth thoſe ſowre and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemous fruites,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>6</hi> Behold, thou loueſt trueth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inward af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections: therefore haſt thou taught me wiſedome in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecrete of mine heart.</note> in ſteade of that ſynceritie and puritie which thou requireſt not onely outward, but to be reſident in the hidden ſpirite and heart: and yet there was no want in thee, O moſt good and gentle God, that this vntowardneſſe was not corrected, ſith thou taughteſt me thy wiſedome, and that not after a common cuſtomarie facion, but learning me apart, and making my ſpirite capable of thy moſt rare and exquiſite myſteries, ſuch as thou reuealeſt not to euery one. Nowe then Lorde,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>7</hi> Purge me with hyſſope, &amp; I ſhalbe cleame: waſh me, &amp; I ſhalbe whiter the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſnowe.</note> what is to be done?</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <hi>7</hi> Behold on the one ſide a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſande maledictions, which I haue notably deſerued: on the other part an infinite deapth of thy mercies, whereof thou haſt giuen mee ſure
<pb facs="tcp:20964:38"/>pledges in thy lawe ſacrifices. For it is not in vayne, nor by mans in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention, that in ſolemne ſacrifices, blood is ſprinckled with hyſope. I haue bene wet therewith, O Lord, by chy commaundement, but retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to my foule vncleanneſſe, I am verely become leprous within: And therefore Lord, take that very hyſope, which is the ſacrament of the liuely power &amp; force of that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice ſo long looked for, and waſh me with the true blood of Chriſt, which ſhalbe ſhedde in the ordayned time, for cleanſing of all iniquitie. Waſhe me, ſprinckle me, and rubbe me on all ſides with this hyſope &amp; this blood, the alone very meane to doe away the loathſome and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prous blotte of ſinne: ſo ſhall I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come neate and white as ſnowe, whereas nowe I am thus vile and
<pb facs="tcp:20964:39"/>ſtinking before thee and the world.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>8</hi> Make me to heare ioy and gladneſſe, that the bones, which thou haſt bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, may reioyce.</note>
                  <hi>8</hi> Alacke, you ſo many delights and heauenly contentments, which were wont to reioyce my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, cauſing me to finde reſt in the middeſt of all dolours, where are you nowe? O Lord, reſtore them to me, making me to heare thy voyce of abſolution for my ſinnes, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting my poore conſcience mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally wounded, and ſoundly ſetting together and knitting my bones, which are broken all to ſhiuers.</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>9</hi> Hide thy face from my ſinnes, and put away all mine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities.</note>
                  <hi>9</hi> My God, turne away that eye and looke which is ſo terrible and inſupportable, when thou wilt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider ſinnes, and chiefely my ſinnes ſo great and ſo many: Rather wipe them away Lorde, let not one of them remayne, ſo as they may neuer come in accompt before thee.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20964:39"/>
               <p n="10">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>10</hi> Create in me a cleane heart, O God, and</note>
                  <hi>10</hi> Lord, thou haddeſt once by thy ſingular bountie changed mee and renewed me by the great and onely grace of thy ſpirite, hauing framed mine vnderſtanding to know thee, my iudgement to approue thee, my will to loue thee, and to take plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in thy commaundementes ſo pure &amp; holy: At once, thou haddeſt made me a newe creature. But into what darkeneſſe haue I turned this light? I haue marred all, I haue deſtroyed and ouerturned all, and therefore, O God, beginne againe as it were anewe thy worke: be the creator of this inwarde man nowe the ſecond time,<note place="margin">renue a right ſpirit within me.</note> ſpreading forth thy force ſuch as may pearce to the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of me, that thou mayeſt forme in me (as it were) a newe ſoule, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting all ſinne, giuen to whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is good and right.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20964:40"/>
               <p n="11">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>11</hi> Caſt me not away from thy preſence, &amp; take not thine holy Spirite from me.</note>
                  <hi>11</hi> I wote well, I am altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnworthie that thou ſhouldeſt lay any hand againe to me: but, my God, reiect me not, neither depriue mee of all that feeling which thou haddeſt once giuen me, and whereof thou dideſt neuer as yet wholy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaue me. For I know and beleeue my ſelfe to bee of the nomber of thoſe whome thou wilt not looſe, though I haue deſerued to be quite cut off.</p>
               <p n="12">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>12</hi> Reſtore to me the ioy of thy ſaluation, &amp; ſtabliſh me with thy free Spirit</note>
                  <hi>12</hi> Rather my God, in ſteade of taking quite from mee all that reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due which thy goodneſſe hath yet left mee, reſtore mee that againe, whereof my ſinnes haue ſpoyled me, and ſettle mee once more in the aſſurance of my ſaluation, that moſt vnſpeakeable pleaſure and ioye which thou beſtoweſt vpon thy children.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20964:40"/>
               <p n="13">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>13</hi> Then ſhall I teache thy wapes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked,</note>
                  <hi>13</hi> Nowe for ſo much as thou haſt layde on my ſhoulders this ſo weightie, and withall ſo honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a charge of gouerning thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, may it pleaſe thee henceforth to impart me of thy ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, and thoſe ſpeciall graces neceſſary to ſuch a calling, wherein is requiſite that I haue wiſedome, ſkill, high courage and conſtancie, and generally eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry other vertue, not alone for mine owne vſe, but alſo for the conduct of this folke committed to mee.<note place="margin">and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners ſhalbe conuerred vnto thee. <hi>14</hi> Deliuer me from blood, O god, which art y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> God of my ſa'<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, &amp; my tongue ſhall ſing iofyully of thy righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe.</note> Then in ſteade of ſuch lewde exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples I haue giuen, I ſhall not ſpare to ſhewe foorth both in deede and worde the right way to others, and ſhalbe thine inſtrument to fetch home to thee thoſe that runne riote the furtheſt out.</p>
               <p n="14">
                  <hi>14</hi> O God, O God, who onely canſt and wilt deliuer out of the
<pb facs="tcp:20964:41"/>bondes of ſinne and death, haue pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie on this murderer embrued with innocent blood, and guyltie of a thouſand deaths, and vouchſafe this mouth the grace to ſing howe true thou art in thy promiſes.</p>
               <p n="15">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>15</hi> Open thou my lippes, O Lord, &amp; my mouth ſhal ſhewe forth thy praiſe.</note>
                  <hi>15</hi> Oh, that thy mercy, Lorde, woulde open this mouth which my ſinnes haue ſhut vpon me: for what haue ſinners to doe to ſpeake of thee? But remooue this ſtoppe, and then not hauing any other meane to recogniſe ſo great a benefite, but ſuch as can adde nothing to thee, who art in thy ſelfe abſolutely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, to wit, the ſacrifice of thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>16</hi> For thou deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt no ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, though I would giue it: thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liteſt not in burnt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fring.</note> I ſhall prayſe thee with full mouth, according as thou haſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen me maruailous great occaſion.</p>
               <p n="16">
                  <hi>16</hi> For as to thoſe ſacrifices which ſmoke vpon thine altar, Lord, it is not in them, where thou
<pb facs="tcp:20964:41"/>wilt haue vs ſtaye: There muſt be another maner of oblation to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe thine ire, and a price of better value for my ranſome, yea theſe my faultes being not of the nomber of thoſe, for which thou haſt ordayned thoſe ordinarie ſacrifices. It is thou, Lorde, which muſt prouide that price in thy good ſeaſon, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto alone I holde me confidently, offering thee yet in meane while that ſelfe ſame thing,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>17</hi> The ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices of God are a contrite ſpirit: a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite and a broken heart, O God, thou wilt not deſpiſe.</note> which thou haſt giuen mee, and the which I knowe thou of thy grace doeſt not reiect, but doeſt rather receiue it in ſo good part, as without it all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde ſeruice diſpleaſeth thee, to witte, a ſpirite throughly humbled by ſenſe of ſinne, an heart con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite, brayed, and grounde with apprehenſion of thy iuſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20964:42"/>
               <p n="18">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>18</hi> Be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourable vnto Zion for thy good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: build the walles of Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.</note> 
                  <hi>18</hi> What more my God? wilt thou for this indignation which thou haſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceyued againſt my miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deedes, that this worke which I haue begunne by thine ordinance, ſhould remayne vnfiniſhed? Shall thine owne mountaine of Sion, thy holy dwelling Ieruſalem bee left thus vnperfect, becauſe Dauid made himſelfe vnworthy to laye to his ſo foule handes? No, Lorde, thy good pleaſure can not bee of that minde. This buylding was orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of thee, becauſe thou ſo woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>19</hi> Then ſhalt thou accept the ſacrifices of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, euen the burnt offring and oblation: then ſhall they offer talues vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thine altar.</note> alſo Lord, thou ſhalt finiſhe it, as in trueth it is thy worke, and not of men.</p>
               <p n="19">
                  <hi>19</hi> Then both I, who haue thus groſſely fayled, and my people whome thou haſt chaſtiſed by ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king thy Spirite from their king, ſhall all ſee the effect of thy mercy,
<pb facs="tcp:20964:42"/>that is to ſaye, thy ſeruice well and rightly ſet vp, the oblations made as appertayneth, the altars ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king according to the rule by thee ordayned, euen a moſt certaine te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie of that fauour which thou ſhalt haue ſhewed to thy poore ſeruant Dauid, and to thy people. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:20964:43"/>
               <head>Beza vpon the A meditation vpon the 102 Pſalme.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>1</hi> O Lorde, heare my prayer, and let my cry come vnto thee.</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Eternal God, it is now high tyme for thee to heare the prayer of thy poore deſolate Church, whoſe diſtreſſes ſithe they force her not to ſpeake, but to cry with a full voyce, let not her crie vaniſh in the aire, but come to thee, who art e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery where to heare ſuch as call to thee.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>2</hi> Hide not thy face from mee in the time of my trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: incline thine eares vnto me: when I call, make haſte to heare me.</note> 
                  <hi>2</hi> The darke day of affliction is come: alas, caſt vpon mee thy looke of compaſſion, that may ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this moſt thicke darkneſſe. Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, O my God, my rude vnman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerlineſſe, and beare with mee that in this preſſing neede I once more pray the bending of thine eare, and thy ſpeede to make mee feele howe
<pb facs="tcp:20964:43"/>thou haſt heard me, anſwering mee by the experience of thy bountie and mercie.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>3</hi> For my dayes are conſumed like ſmoke, and my bones are burnt like an herth.</note>
                  <hi>3</hi> Alas, time was when I was faire &amp; floriſhing vnder thy fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable gentleneſſe, now am I not ſo, my good dayes are paſt, as a ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vapour: I haue bene mightie and in flower of my ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth againſt all aſlaultes within and without, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biding ſtill faſt by meanes of thine vnderpropping and ſtay: nowe my bones are cracked and weare into duſt, as if they had bene ſeared and burned like lime in a kilne.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>4</hi> Mine heart is ſmitten &amp; withereth like graſſe, becauſe I forgate to eate my bread.</note>
                  <hi>4</hi> That wonted courage ſo ſtoute againſt Sathan and his complices, is now withered as haye, and dryed like graſſe cut down by the mower. I had, alas, ſo good an appetite and fedde my ſelfe hungerly with that ſo nouriſhing, ſo ſweete, and ſo
<pb facs="tcp:20964:44"/>delicate viande wherewith thou di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt furniſh vs from aboue, and I dranke in ſo great draughtes of that ſo precious and well reliſed liquor of thy quickening water: Nowe finde I a dearth of this bread, and the ſmall remaine that I haue ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, goeth downe with mee againſt the ſtomacke, ſo low am I brought, and haue loſt my taſte.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>5</hi> For the voyce of any gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning my bones do cleaue to my ſkinne.</note>
                  <hi>5</hi> The ayre was wont to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſounde from Eaſt to Weſt, thoſe ſonnets of gladneſſe, whereof thou dideſt miniſter to mee both the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and the making. Nowe the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens and the earth doe ring of my lamentable cryes, woe begone that I am lying on the ground,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>6</hi> I am like a peli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cane of the wildernes: I am like an owle of the deſerts.</note> and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing like her that hath nothing left, but the ſkinne bounde to the bones.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>6</hi> There was no quarter of the
<pb facs="tcp:20964:44"/>worlde where I was not lodged in palaces moſt beautifull and prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which thou haddeſt ſo well foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, buylded, and trimmed for mee: in which I tooke pleaſure to ſee thee in thy great beautie, and to be recreated with thy moſt cleare and cheerefull voyce, (in deede a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly happineſſe:) Nowe nothing is to be ſeene but ruines, in which hardly can I diſcrye ſome appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of that which hath bene: eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where are horrible deſertes, hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deous caues, wherein nothing is heard but the howlings of ſhricke owles, night rauens, and ſuch like dolefull and vnlucky blacke night birdes.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>7</hi> I watch and am as a ſparowe alone vpon the houſe top.</note>
                  <hi>7</hi> And I poore ſoule, wandring through thickeſt of this deſert, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing no reſt day nor night, I dwell all alone, hatching my griefes at a
<pb facs="tcp:20964:45"/>venture vnder couert of ſuch ſmall retraict as I may light vpon. Alack, I hurt no body, yea I ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der good for euill:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>8</hi> Mine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies</note> yet in ſteade that my deſolation ſhoulde cleaue the heart of the moſt hardened, and mooue the felleſt of them, if not to relieue me, at leaſt not to perſecute me further. I ſee nothing but ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies rounde about mee, and what maner enemies: Firſt, that great deuouring Lyon, which hath ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, torne, and ſwallowed ſo many of my poore children from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the worlde: Then thoſe Inchanters which by their colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red wordes and reaſons, in very deede vnreaſonable, ſet together by their bibble habble, haue ſuborned very many of my childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yea, ſome of the beſt wittes of my companie. Thoſe ſnares of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, wolues
<pb facs="tcp:20964:45"/>maſking like paſtours, paunches belching out ſacriledges, deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, O God, thy people as bread, ſmallowing vp the poore widowes and orphanes vnder ſhadowe of prayer. What ſhall I ſay, Lord, of them that are yet worſe, to witte, theſe curſed ones, which gnawe mee within my bowels, theſe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques, murderers, rending in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces the members from the bodie, whereof thou art head? Very ſoule quellers, coniured enemies againſt thy trueth, turners vpſide downe of thy right wayes, mouthes for the father of lyes, folke without ſhame or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, raſers vnder the name of buylders: to bee ſhort, the moſt pernitious enemies that I haue. Alas, this is not all, there is no crime which they laye not to my charge,<note place="margin">reuile me dayly,</note> no rage which exerciſeth
<pb facs="tcp:20964:46"/>not it ſelfe againſt mee: I am the daughter of peace, and yet charge they me as mother and nource of al hurliburlies that toſſe and tomble the world. Patience is my marke, and yet I am accuſed as a ſtirrer of all ſedition: I keepe a ſchoole of all trueth, yet am I condemned as a lyar, and the fountaine of leaſings: I praye for my very enemies, yet will they needes make me vengea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and irreconcilable. O my bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed children, whoſe ſoules by the crueltie of my deſperate enemies haue bene thruſt into heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> through all ſortes of torments, and of whom the worlde was not worthie, ioyne your teſtimonies before the eternal God, vnto the complaintes of your poore widowe mother languiſhing yet in earth. O earth drunken with the blood of mine innocent childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:
<pb facs="tcp:20964:46"/>ye waters, whoſe ſtreames haue bene oft ſtopped, and their hue chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by the poore murdered bodies: O ayre, which haſt receyued ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of their grones and ſighes: yee flames which haue conſumed ſo many martyrs to the trueth: yee ſmordes, which haue wounded, hewen, and chopt off ſo many of my members, are ye not ſufficient wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes to me, that I complayne not without moſt iuſt cauſe? And yet my God, it is not of thee that I thus playne me: for, if I looke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the faults of my children, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that what rigor ſoeuer they haue felt, that yet thy mercie ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mountes thy iudgement: And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering on the other ſide, that the wicked doe not hate and perſecute me but for thy name, and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I am made like vnto my deare
<pb facs="tcp:20964:47"/>and alone ſpouſe, thy welbeloued Sonne. Oh father, ſo farre am I from complayning, that contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe this croſſe is to me a moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and pretious teſtimonie, that thou chaſtiſeſt mee as a father, and loueſt mee with the ſame loue, wherewith thou loueſt my ſpouſe, with whome being crucified, I am likewiſe ſure to raygne. To bee ſhort, wherein can I deeme my ſelf honourable, but in thy croſſe? for, to bee hated of the worlde for thy ſake, is a goodly teſtimonie, that a man is not of the worlde: and to drinke in the cuppe of his Lorde, is one of the greateſt honours that the ſeruant can receiue. But alas, I ſee and confeſſe, that what the wicked doe vniuſtly, thou doeſt it iuſtly for the iniquitie of moſt part of my riotous children, it being a thing
<pb facs="tcp:20964:47"/>right reaſonable, that the bringing into order beginne at thine owne houſe, and that they which haue leaſt excuſe, bee with the firſt moſt rigorouſly chaſtiſed. Moreouer, my God, what cauſe haue I to put on all my wayling weede,<note n="9" place="margin">Surely I haue eaten aſhes as bread, and mingled my drinke w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wéeping, <hi>10</hi> Becauſe of thine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation and thy wrath: for thou haſt heaued me vp, and caſt mee downe. <hi>11</hi> My dayes are like a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe that fadeth, and I am wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered like, graſſe.</note> ſeeing thy holy name ſo blaſphemed, thine houſe prophaned, robbed, ruined, and brought into aſhes, thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie giuen into the handes of ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies?</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <hi>9</hi> Loe why I lye on the earth, liuing on the duſt in ſtead of meate, and teares for drinke, through the deepe conceyuing of this moſt hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible indignation, and this ſo iuſt diſpleaſure againſt mee, whome thou haſt thus ouerthrowen, from a ſtate wherein thou hadeſt ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exalted mee, in ſo much as I goe fading away, and loſt as a ſhadowe
<pb facs="tcp:20964:48"/>at Sunne fall, and am there as cut downe graſſe without force or liuelineſſe.</p>
               <p n="12">
                  <note n="12" place="margin">But thou, O Lord, doeſt remayne for euer, &amp; thy remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce from generation to genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>
                  <hi>12</hi> But what? yet am I not out of heart, O mightie and eternall God, when I conſider that thou art for euer the ſame, and that it can not be otherwiſe, but the memorie of thy renoume muſt be euer dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. For, this preſuppoſed, albeit thou art not vnderpropped but of thy ſelfe,<note n="13" place="margin">Thou wilt ariſe &amp; haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy vpon Zion: for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time to haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy thereon, for the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted time is come.</note> and that nothing may bee put too, or taken from thee: Yet, ſith it hath liked thee to choſe from out of the vnworthieſt creature, to wit, man, a certaine number, which is thy Church, there to make thine infinite glory for euer to ſhine: I conclude with my ſelfe, that of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie (howſoeuer it ſeemes ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times otherwiſe) as thou haſt bene caſt downe in thy Church, nowe
<pb facs="tcp:20964:48"/>lying on the grounde, ſo wilt thou rayſe againe thy ſelfe, in vprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring her, and all for thy great pitie and compaſſion ſake. In deede, Lord, thou haſt ſo promiſed, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a time effected it. For, into what ſtreights was thy Church brought during that horrible ſlauerie of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, their pilgrimage in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, their calamities befalling them vnder the Iudges, the capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie of thine Arke, the renting of Iudah and Iſrael, the dreadfull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction by Babel, when there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayned not one ſtone vpon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: thine holy Temple was made an heape of duſt, the ſacred veſſels were ſacrilegiouſly rauined, caried away, and profanely abuſed: thy ſacrificers murdered, the crowne of Dauid tombled to the grounde, all the lande dyed with blood,
<pb facs="tcp:20964:49"/>without regarde of age, ſexe, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree: the ſmall reſidue dragged in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to bondage among all the nations of the worlde, vnder ſo many cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, among the Syrians and Egyptians: and aboue al, when thy temple being reedified, thou depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedſt out of it, and gaueſt roome as it were to Idoles in thine owne pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laces: and when thy lawe, I ſaye, thy moſt ſacred lawe was ſo villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſly interdicted, torne, and burnt, and as it were, quite abrogated by conſent of moſt part of thy people iuſtly abandoned of thee? Nowe after this horrible and dreadfull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of mine auncient children thus cut off, and when thou gaueſt mee a newe generation, alas, of what rages and cruelties had I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment for the ſpace of three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of yeeres one after another?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20964:49"/>
               <p n="14">
                  <note n="14" place="margin">For thy ſeruantes delight in the ſtones therof, and haue pitie on the duſt thereof.</note>
                  <hi>14</hi> Yet euer at mine extremeſt neede thou dideſt ſende mee Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions, and madeſt me to finde force in feebleneſſe, calme in tempeſt, fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie in miſery, life in death: Thou dideſt, I ſay, euermore cauſe mee to ſee what differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce there is betwene that fatherly rodde wherewith thou correcteſt thy children to ſaluation, &amp; that yron barre wherewith thou daſheſt thine enemies paſt all reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie. Egypt, Niniue, Babel, and this loftie image of the monarchies teared by my ruines, and cymented with my childrens blood, are nowe come downe, while yet thy poore Sion ſtandes and ſpeakes. Thou, O God, euermore moſt like thy ſelfe, nowe that thou ſeeſt me more ſtreyghted then euer, ſhewe that thou haſt ſet boundes to my miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, as thou dideſt in olde time to
<pb facs="tcp:20964:50"/>thoſe captiuities of Egypt and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon. Rayſe vp ſome Ioſuahs, and Eſdras, ſome Nehemiahs and Conſtantines, which may reare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine thy raſed palaces, taking pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie on our ruines and ſackinges. Aboue all, Lord, ſende vs ſome Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons and ſome Eſdras, hauing thy ſpirite in their heart, and thy worde in their mouth, as true inſtruments of thy power, to rayſe againe this thy ſpirituall buylding which is throwen to the grounde, and ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figured, as with much a doe can a man tracke out ſo much as the very auncient foundation: And bleſſe, Lorde,<note n="15" place="margin">Then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heathen ſhal feare the Name of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, and all the kings of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth thy glory.</note> the hande and the labours of thy faithfull workemen, ſo as in ſteade of ſo many peoples at this day reuolted from thee, ſome for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by Mahomet, others ſeduced by falſe paſtors, profaning the chayre
<pb facs="tcp:20964:50"/>of trueth by their coyned and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfaited doctriues,<note n="16" place="margin">When y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde ſhall buylde vp Zion, and ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in his glory,</note> all may bee brought backe againe to thee, in ſuch wiſe, that thy glory may ſhine more then euer,<note n="17" place="margin">And ſhal turne vnto the prayer of the deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, &amp; not deſpiſe their praier</note> and thy heauenly Sion, that workemanſhip of thine owne very hande, may be lifted vp againe to her former brightneſſe.</p>
               <p n="17">
                  <hi>17</hi> Heare, O mightie God, the prayer of thy poore deſolate daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,<note n="18" place="margin">This ſhall bee written for the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to come: and the people, which ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be created, ſhall prayſe the Lord.</note> yet ſo much cheriſhed of thee.</p>
               <p n="18">
                  <hi>18</hi> Giue me matter to couche in my recordes this moſt excellent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance, to the ende that the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie may dure without ende, and that this people beyng throughly renewed,<note n="19" place="margin">For hee hath looked down from the height of his ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuarie: out of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen did the Lorde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde the earth.</note> may haue occaſion to magnifie thy prayſe from father to ſonne.</p>
               <p n="19">
                  <hi>19</hi> Bring againe that golden worlde, wherein one may ſaye with better ſpeede then euer, that thou,
<pb facs="tcp:20964:51"/>O eternall God, being ſet in thy high throne, aduaunced aboue the heyghtes of heauens, haſt caſt thy cheerefull &amp; gracious eye vpon the earth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>20</hi> That he might heare the mourning of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer the children of death:</note> giuing eare to the grones of thy languiſhing captiue Church, and of thy poore children looking for nothing but the ſlaughter.</p>
               <p n="21">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>21</hi> That they may declare the name of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde in Lion, &amp; his prayſe in Ieruſalem.</note>
                  <hi>21</hi> Gather againe together, Lord, the ſheepe wildly ſtraying and ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered through the wilderneſſe, full of hungerbitten and ſtarke wood Lyons and Tygers.</p>
               <p n="22">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>22</hi> When the people ſhall be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes to ſerue the Lord.</note>
                  <hi>22</hi> Vnite againe to thee the realmes which Sathan hath with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawen, ſith thou art King of kings, to whome all glorie, puiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunce, and magnificence belongs. Let thy name be called on, and thy prayſe proclaymed in Ieruſalem in ſight and knowledge of all the worlde.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20964:51"/>
               <p n="23">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>23</hi> He a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated my ſtrength in the way, &amp; ſhortened my dayes.</note>
                  <hi>23</hi> Well then, I haue bene af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted a thouſande and a thouſande ſortes, my courſe hath bene cutte in two, my dayes haue bene, as it were ſhortened:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>24</hi> And I ſayd, O my God, take me not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way in the middes of my dayes: thy yeeres endure from gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to generation</note> I haue bene conſtrayned to beſeeche my God, that he would not plucke me away with ſuch vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and that he would ſuffer mee to finiſh my rare: But conſidering the eternitie of my God, for euer himſelfe, this chaunge doeth no longer amaze mee, knowing that my foundations are layde farre more ſurely, then if they were but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triſed by the heauen or by the earth:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>25</hi> Thou haſt afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time layde the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dion of the earth, &amp; the heauens are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> work of thine handes.</note> For, though the earth be ſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſetled by the maruailous pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of him that layde the foundation, and that this heauenly frame, the very workemanſhippe of the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall God, hath neuer yet ſwerued among ſo many, ſo violent, and
<pb facs="tcp:20964:52"/>continuall reuolutions, yet al with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in meaſure and compaſſe ſo exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>6 They <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>al periſh, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>alt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>re: euen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ey al ſhal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>axe olde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> doeth a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rment: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> a veſture <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>lt thou <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>m, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y ſhalbe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nged. But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>u art y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>e, &amp; thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>es ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> fayle. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>dren of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>l con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>e, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſeede <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſtande in thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> as none can amende: Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe muſt all this geare paſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way one daye, it being ſo determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: and this goodly ſhewe ſhall va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh as wee ſee a garment by litle and litle waxe old and weare away. But thou, O mightie God, abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute in thy ſelfe, haſt neyther ende nor beginning, but exempting thy ſelfe from all chaunge, thou decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt thy power in the varietie of thy workes.</p>
               <p n="28">
                  <hi>28</hi> And for ſo much as I am ſtayed vpon this thy permanent power, &amp; vnchangeable good will, aſſured, I ſaye, vpon that throne, whereof thy Sonne my redeemer hath taken poſſeſſion, to make mee his coheire through the mercy, inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie, obedience, ſatiſfaction and
<pb facs="tcp:20964:52"/>merite wherewith he purchaſed me the celeſtiall kingdome: I am cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly reſolued, that this ſtayedneſſe will vpholde mee, and that through all the tempeſtes, by which it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth thee to leade mee, for the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of thy bountie and power in conſeruation of thine, I ſhall yet arriue in that eternal hauen, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in all we, whome thou alloweſt for thy ſeruantes, though neuer ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable, beyng borne age after age, and whome thou ſhalt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge for true children of Abraham, Iſaak, and Iacob, with whom thou contractedſt the couenant of eternall life, ſhal haue our dwelling worlde without ende, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:20964:53"/>
               <head>A meditation vpon the 130 Pſalme.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>1</hi> Out of the deepe places.</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> My poore ſoule, fall not flatte downe, vexe not thy ſelfe out of meaſure: the burden of thy ſinnes preſſeth thee ſore in deede, but bee not for al that, quite ouerwhelmed: thou art thruſt downe ſo low into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deepeſt deepes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou hadeſt neede cry lowde for to bee heard of him, which dwelleth in the hygheſt heights: And the euer burning hell fire is not farre from that lake, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thine iniquities haue plunged thee, ſo as thou mayeſt, as it were, perceiue the Echo of their cryes &amp; deſperat howlings, which be there caft without al hope of euer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming forth. But the Lord which bringes euen to the borders of hell his beſt
<pb facs="tcp:20964:53"/>beloued, when they forget them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, knowes alſo howe well to bring them backe again. Goe no further then downward, but lift vp thine heart together with thy crye, and ſaye not in thy ſelfe, God hath reiected mee from before him, for, ſuch la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>guage God likes not. Thou cryeſt vnto God, and wherefore, but onely becauſe hee hath awake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thee? For loe, what he cryeth in thine eares: My people, what haue I done to thee? or wherein haue I grieued or yrked thee?<note place="margin">haue I called vnto thee, O Lorde.</note> O my God, what ſhall I anſwere thee hereto? He which receyueth the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, goeth firſt about to excuſe him: The Iudge falleth a beſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the guyltie partie: and what can I ſay, my God, but that I can not comprehende that which thou doeſt for me, who could not ſo
<pb facs="tcp:20964:54"/>much as haue any being, hadeſt not thou made mee? And after thou ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt made mee, either I forgat all that thou hadeſt done for mee, or els the remembrance thereof repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vnto mee mine vnthankeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, aſtoniſheth my ſenſe, and ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth my mouth. Rather thou thy ſelfe Lord, declare vnto me what thou haſt done for mee, ſo as I may neure forget it. Thou madeſt mee of nothing in the perſon of my firſt father, and is it not ſomewhat to be made ſomewhat of nothing? Thou haſt facioned mee in my mothers wombe, thou haſt taken mee from thence, as it were by thine owne proper handes: thou haſt ſuckled, nouriſhed and brought mee vp, by rayſing vp vnto mee ſuch as did it according to that will and habilitie, which thou gaueſt them. Through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="tcp:20964:54"/>this infancie, from howe many harmes didſt thou defend me? In ſo much as I owe thee euen ſo many liues, as I haue paſſed dayes and houres, minutes and moments: and yet during all that age, I neyther could knowe my ſelfe, whereby to know how much I ought thee, nor yet thee, whereby to thanke thee for it. What other thing then did ſtirre thee to do well by me, but onely thy goodneſſe? Paſſing further on in yeeres, mine vnworthineſſe grewe on together with mine age, and thy largeſſe on the other ſide grewe ſo much the more, hauing beſtowed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly on mee not onely witte, health, and ſo many other giftes of vſe in this life, which alſo thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoweſt liberally ſometime on thy greateſt enemies: but thou haſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted to mee the knowledge of thy
<pb facs="tcp:20964:55"/>ſauing health by thy deare Sonne our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt: Thou comfortedſt me in a thouſand afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, thou haſt borne with mee in tenne thouſande ſinnes, thou haſt vpholden me in innumerable temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations: ſhortly, thou neuer ceaſedſt by thy bountie to fight againſt my malice, and againſt my rebellion by thy patience. Loe, what thou haſt done to me, Lorde: Nowe what is it that I haue done againe? Alas, my God,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2</hi> Lorde, heare my voyce: let thine eares attend to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> voyce of my pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</note> if I enter into this deapth of ripping vp mine iniquities, whereof any one ſufficeth to make me guiltie of eternall death, ſurely I am quite vndone.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>3</hi> If thou, O Lorde, ſtraightly markeſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquities, O Lord, who ſhal ſtand?</note> 
                  <hi>2</hi> I can then doe nothing elſe, but beſeeche thee to heare my cries: and thou wilt do it, Lorde. For, O Lorde God, who coulde euer haue abiden before thee, if thou, hadeſt
<pb facs="tcp:20964:55"/>taken the lawe on his ſinnes?</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>4</hi> But mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy is with thee, that thou mayſt be feared.</note>
                  <hi>4</hi> Take heart againe, my ſoule, for thy Iudge is the fountaine of compaſſion, otherwiſe there were none order to ſerue and beſeeche him, but all in vaine. It is true, thou haſt lauiſhed out his riches, but thy God is as riche, and as farre from nigardlineſſe as euer: Thou haſt thralled thy ſelfe to ſinne and death, but thy God hath redeemed thee with a more then ſufficient ranſom: Saye rather with that poore vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrift,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>5</hi> I haue wayted on the Lorde: my ſoule hath way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and I haue truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his worde.</note> I goe to my father: hee will receiue thee without caſting thee in the teeth, yea rather he will reioyce of thy returne, hee wayteth to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace thee with his mercy. Doe not as did Adam, who ranne away from his face whome hee had offended: Should the ſicke man flee the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition? Whither ſhoulde a poore
<pb facs="tcp:20964:56"/>body goe, but to him that will and can helpe him? Hee hath giuen his Sonne for thee, and will he nowe reiect thee? Weeneſt thou that Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, who hath bought thee ſo deere,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>6</hi> My ſoule waiteth on the Lorde more then the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning watch watcheth for the morning.</note> wil now loſe thee? Waite for his grace rather, and if hee be ſlowe to reache his hande, conſider that thou ſlackeſt much more thy tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to him. Doubt not of his wil, ſith both in his worde, and in his dealing towardes thee, thou haſt yet more cleare and euident teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies thereof, then thou haſt of his might. Be rather in thy warde, watching alwayes, without being weary or ſlumbering,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>7</hi> Let Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el waite on Lord: for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> with the Lorde is mercie, and with him is great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</note> vntill he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare as the dawning of the day, chaſing away the darkeneſſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thou art plunged.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <hi>7</hi> And you whoſoeuer, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen like mee, followe mine
<pb facs="tcp:20964:56"/>example and aduiſe, goe we all my brethren to that great eternall God, ioyning together with the acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement of our faultes, hope, which neuer diſappoynteth them that haue it, being ſetled vpon his infallible trueth. If our ſinnes bee innumerable, his mercie is infinite towardes the repenting, beleeuing, hoping, and praying.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>8</hi> And he ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déeme Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael from all his ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities.</note>
                  <hi>8</hi> Will wee haue any other proofe hereof, then that incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible loue, wherethrough this good father was mooued, euen not to ſpare his ſonne? Then this infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite loue of this great ſhepheard, which made himſelfe of none ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt, to enriche vs? Who hath charged himſelf with al our ſinnes, not one except? Who was obedient for his poore Iſrael, that is to ſaye, his elect, euen to that death of the
<pb facs="tcp:20964:57"/>croſſe? I embrace thee with both mine armes, O Ieſus Chriſt, which haſt reconciled me to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, aſſuring me by thy Spirite, of the comfort of my ſaluation in thee, and ſo faſt embracing thee, I receiue the pledges of life and euerlaſting bliſſe. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:20964:57"/>
               <head>A meditation vpon the 143 Pſalme.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>1</hi> Heare my prayer, O Lorde, and hearken vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to my ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication: anſwere me in thy trueth &amp; in thy righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes.</note>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Eternall God, liſten to my prayer, hearken to my requeſt, heare mee, for thyne aſſured truſtines byndeth thee to holde that which thy goodnes hath promiſed: And what can I alleadge herein, but thyne owne ſelfe? for not I alone,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2</hi> (And en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter not into iudgement with thy ſeruant: for in thy ſight ſhall none that liueth be iuſtified)</note> poore and woe begone ſinner that I am, but no man aliue going about to debate his cauſe with thee, as though he had right on his ſide, ſhal be found righteous. Wherefore, in ſtead of pleading I condemne and iudge my ſelf: I bring thee nothing of myne owne but iniquitie, and I craue that which is thyne, to wit, grace and mercy.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20964:58"/>
               <p n="3">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>3</hi> For the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie hath perſecuted my ſoule: hee hath ſmitten my life downe to the earth: he hath layde me in the darkenes, as they that haue bene dead long ago:</note> 
                  <hi>3</hi> O my God, thou ſeeſt, alas, my piteous eſtate: myne enemyes and thyne purſue me for life, which already lyeth as is were in the duſt, at their mercy: I am euen nowe in the darkenes of death, yea I am as a Carion long ſince dead and ſtink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4</hi> Alas, my ſpirit is ſo perplexed, that it cannot reſolue nor winde it ſelfe out.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>4</hi> And my ſpirit was in perplexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in me, &amp; mine heart within mee was ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</note> Both vnderſtanding and hart are quite loſt within me: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon I bethought mee of ſo many auncient teſtimonyes and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which I haue had of thy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nignitie and fauour from mine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancie, and I ſtayde my ſelfe vpon conſideration of the high workes of thy handes, euen true euidences of thine infinite wiſedome and bounty together, towardes the very leaſt of thy creatures: and namely I beheld
<pb facs="tcp:20964:58"/>in my ſpirit thine high actes on be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of thy welbeloued,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>6</hi> I ſtretch forth mine hands vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee: my ſoule deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth after thee, as the thirſtie la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</note> things ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily paſſing all wonder.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>6</hi> This incouraged me, my God, to ſtretche foorth myne handes to thee: this I ſay,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>7</hi> Heare me ſpeedily, O Lorde, for my ſpirite fayleth: hide not thy face from me, elſe I ſhall be like vnto them that goe downe into the pit</note> ſtrengthened my poore conſcience to addreſſe it ſelfe to thee, yea with more burning de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, then euer the moſt parched ground gaped for the moyſture of thy rayne.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <hi>7</hi> But what is to be done? Euen forthwith haſte thee, anſwere me O eternal God,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>8</hi> Let mee heare thy louing kind<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes in the morning, for in thee is my truſt: ſhewe me the way, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I ſhould walke in, for I lift vp my ſoule vnto thee.</note> for I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> endure no longer: Beholde me dead, lying in the duſt of the graue, vnleſſe thou ſhew forth that cheerefull eye which with one onely looke can reuiue the dead: without the ſound of thy moſt gentle voyce, I am caſt away: make it then to ſounde and ſound agayne in mine eares, &amp; in mine heart, for
<pb facs="tcp:20964:59"/>I am of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> number of thoſe to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou haſt bound thy ſelfe, no whit, alas, for any merit of mine, but thine only free mercy. I am, I ſay, one of thoſe by thy grace, to wit, of thoſe which hope for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which thou haſt promiſed, &amp; giuen them grace to beleeue: without this I wot not where to become, nor which way to turne me. And therefore, O high God, I prepare my ſelfe to thee, that thou mighteſt teache me which way to holde:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>9</hi> Deliuer me, O Lord, from mine enemies: for I hid mee with thee.</note> thou ſeeſt howe mine enemies hemme me in: deliuer me, O eternall, who alone canſt and wilt do it, for ſo much as I haue no refuge but vnder thy couert. Alas, I weened with my ſelfe to haue ſeene many trim ſtarting holes: &amp; agayne I am tempted to aſſay infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite meanes. But, God forbid, I ſhoulde herein followe that which
<pb facs="tcp:20964:59"/>this blind &amp; froward nature would ſuggeſt. Hence from mee, thou vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe wit, fooliſh wiſedome, vnrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable reaſon, and all ye paſſions which can doe nought but cary me headlong on mine owne heade. It is thou, O Lord, that I will hold, &amp; hold faſt for my God: conſequently,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>10</hi> Teache mee to do thy wil, for thou art my God: let thy good Spirit lead me vnto the land of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note> nothing will I will, ſaue that thou willeſt. And becauſe I can neither vnderſtand this will, nor take plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to followe it when I haue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood it, teach it me, O Lord, and leade me in it, not alone to knowe it, but alſo to practiſe it, Let thy good ſpirit be my loads man in the right way,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>11</hi> Quicken me, O Lord for thy Names take, &amp; for thy righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes bring my ſoule out of trouble.</note> and not that tempting ſpirit, nor yet fleſh and blood.</p>
               <p n="11">
                  <hi>11</hi> Vp nowe then my poore ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit hitherunto deſolate: comfort thy ſelfe, for the eternall will drawe comfort forth of him ſelfe to reuiue
<pb facs="tcp:20964:60"/>ſhee, becauſe it hath pleaſed him that his name ſhould be called vpon in thee, and according to his infinite bounty will deliuer thee out of all anguiſhes.</p>
               <p n="12">
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>12</hi> And for thy mercy ſtay mine enemies, &amp; deſtroy all them that op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe my ſoule: for I am thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant.</note> 
                  <hi>12</hi> Doeth Sathan amaſe thee? hee hath vanquiſhed him for thee. Doth the corruption of thy nature aſtoniſh thee? the ſonne of God ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him ſelfe man hath fully ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified it for thee. Doe thy ſinnes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fright thee which be fruits of this corruption? He hath borne them all vpon the tree, and hath payd for thy diſcharge: which more is, his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe is thine, ſith he himſelfe is thine. Art thou afrayde of men, ſith God is for thee? Doth death af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fray thee? it is vanquiſhed and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into an entry of life. Beholde then all thine enemies ſcattered, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold quite vnder foote, all ſuch as
<pb facs="tcp:20964:60" rendition="simple:additions"/>afflicted thee within and without, becauſe the Lorde alloweth thee for one of his ſeruants and houſhold. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>Imprinted at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> in Bacon houſe by Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtopher Barker, Printer to the Queenes moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Maieſtie. 1582.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20964:61"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20964:61"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
